<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A riche storehouse, or treasurie, for the sicke, full of Christian counsels holesome doctrines, comfortable persuasions, and godly meditations, meete for all Christians, both in sicknesse and in health. Wherevnto is annexed a comfort for poore prisoners, and also an exhortation to repentance. Written in Dutch, by Gaspar Huberine, and Englished by Thomas Godfrie, esquire, late ... fruits and ... at the request of his dangter Marie, wife ... Iohn French, gentleman of the Inner Temple</title>
            <author>Huberinus, Caspar.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 104 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113094</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848334</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848334</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 467:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A riche storehouse, or treasurie, for the sicke, full of Christian counsels holesome doctrines, comfortable persuasions, and godly meditations, meete for all Christians, both in sicknesse and in health. Wherevnto is annexed a comfort for poore prisoners, and also an exhortation to repentance. Written in Dutch, by Gaspar Huberine, and Englished by Thomas Godfrie, esquire, late ... fruits and ... at the request of his dangter Marie, wife ... Iohn French, gentleman of the Inner Temple</title>
                  <author>Huberinus, Caspar.</author>
                  <author>Godfrie, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>101 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [H. Middleton for] Ralph Newberrie, dwelling in Fleetestreat a litle aboue the conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1578.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In four parts. Part 2 caption title reads: How to aduise and comfort them that lye in prison, and be by the magistrate iudgged to dye. Part 3 caption title reads: A faithful and Christian exhortation to repentaunce, and to leade a life in the feare of God. Part 4 caption title reads: An instruction to teache children howe they ought to goe to the Lordes table.</note>
                  <note>A note at the head of part 4 says that it has been adapted to English use.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13420:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13420:1"/>
            <p>A riche Storehouſe, or Treaſurie, for the Sicke, full <hi>of Chriſtian counſels, hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>doctrines, comfortable perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
               </hi> and godly meditations, meete for all Chriſtians, both in ſickneſſe and in health.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Wherevnto is annexed a Comfort for poore Priſoners, and alſo an Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in Dutch, by</hi> Gaſpar Huberine, <hi>and Engliſhed by</hi> THOMAS GODFRIE <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, late Remembrauncer of the firſt Fruits and Tenthes, at the requeſt of his daughter</hi> Marie, <hi>wife vnto</hi> Iohn French, <hi>Gentleman of the Inner</hi> Temple.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>SIRACH. 7.</bibl> ¶ Take pleaſure in viſiting the ſicke: For that will make thee beloued.</q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Ralph Newberrie, dwelling in Fleeteſtreat a litle aboue the Conduit.</p>
            <p>ANNO. 1578.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:13420:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <p>DESIRNA REPOS</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13420:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> noble and moſt vertuous Ladie, the <hi>Ladie Catharine Howard, all temporall</hi> proſperitie in this life, and in the life to come euerlaſting happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worthie and honourable, it is a maruel beyond all maruels, that man, amongeſt all the creatures of this worlde, in his creation ſo ſingular: namely, and onely endued with a reaſonable ſoul, for his ſafetie atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Angels, and aboue al made vnto the image of God: ſo inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly reiecting and forſaking him ſelf, doth ſuffer to be ſnared &amp; inchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the vaine, tranſitorie, and counterfet felicitie of this worlde, griping ſo greedily thereat, as if this carcaſe, beeing ſubiect vnto ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and manifeſt calamities, and in
<pb facs="tcp:13420:3"/> the ende to death and deſtruction, had obteined euerlaſting continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: wheras the ſcripture, to repreſſe oure preſumption, and ſecuritie of life, and to manifeſt our corruption of nature, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually putteth vs in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, that all fleſhe is nothing but graſſe, wormes meate, duſt, and putrifaction: yea, and that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and the goodlieſt of this whole world, with all their ſhewe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, brauerie, and beautie, which men ſo muche adore and imbrace, is but vanitie: and that, if they were weighed in balance with nothing, nothing would bee found heauier then they: then, what manifeſt want of iudgement and ſound knowledge may be thought to be in man, that ſo highly eſteemeth things of ſo ſmall value? whereas, if they would with their inwarde and immortall man, iudge and examine the ende of all
<pb facs="tcp:13420:3"/> things, thereby diſcouering the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of their owne creation, then would they perceiue, that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt bladder puffed vp with the wind of worldly vanitie, is eaſily diſſolued with the ſmaleſt needle of Gods iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: And ſo retire from ſinne full wayes that lead to deſtruction, and indeuour to tread the tracke of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicitie. Meaning, in no wiſe hereby, to perſuade the contempt of the good gifts and bleſsings of God, namely, health, wealth, beautie, and infinitely ſuch others: but warely to vſe them, as Abraham, Iob, Dauid, Iudith, Suſan, with innumerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as gifts not of their own, but of God, giuen for the aduauncement of his glorie, and profite of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to which euery man, what ſo euer, eſpecially is borne: without which ende, muche better had hee neuer beene created: and wiſely
<pb facs="tcp:13420:4"/> to examine the life &amp; end of Diues, who in the eyes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt in this world, but woful wretch that ſo abuſed the good gifts of God, wold haue giuen all, and much more if he might, to haue made exchaunge with Lazarus eſtate, whiche in this worlde was moſt abiect and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. This matter being of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portaunce, then the toung may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, or mans heart may imagine, the rather to moue the dulneſſe of our diſpoſition, hath bene ſet downe by the wiſeſt that euer was amongſt men, in ſpeache and termes no leſſe ſtraunge then maruellous, after this maner: Put away diſpleaſure out of thy heart, and remoue euill from thy body: for childhood &amp; youth is but vanitie. Remember thy maker the ſoner in thy youth, or euer the days of aduerſitie come, and or the yeares drawe nighe, when thou ſhalt ſay, I
<pb facs="tcp:13420:4"/> haue no pleaſure in them, before the Sunne, the light, the Moone &amp; ſtars be darkned, and or the cloudes turne againe after the rayne, when the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the houſe ſhall tremble, when the ſtrong menne ſhall bow them ſelues, and when the millers ſtande ſtill bicauſe they be ſo few, and when the light of the windowes ſhall waxe dim, when the doores in the ſtreates ſhall be ſhut, when the voyce of the miller ſhall be laide downe, when men ſhall riſe vp at the voyce of the birde, &amp; when the daughters of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke ſhalbe brought low, when men ſhall feare in high places, &amp; be afraid in the ſtreates: when the Almond tree ſhall flouriſh, and be laden with the Graſhopper, and when all luſt ſhall paſſe, by cauſe man goeth to his long home, and the mourners go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſtreates: or euer the ſiluer lace be taken away, and or the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:13420:5"/> well bee broken, or the pot bee broken at the well, and the wheele vpon the ciſterne: then ſhall the duſt bee turned againe vnto earth, from whence it came, &amp;c. For as much as theſe certeine and terrible dayes ſhall come vpon vs, when no time may be reuoked, no remorce accepted, no remedie vſed, or any ſuccour obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but by the onely meanes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in this ſmall treatiſe, left into my handes without any patrone, I thought it no leſſe conuenient vnto my bounden duetie, then meete for the viewe of your repoſed minde, to make a preſent thereof vnto your honour, not onely hoping, but alſo moſt humbly beſeching, that it may pleaſe you of your great nobleneſſe, to accept the patronage thereof. Thus crauing pardon for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, I committe your good Ladiſhippe to him, who is plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:13420:5"/> in all good graces and bleſſed giftes, beſeeching him, in this life, to be your chiefeſt riches, and in the life to come, your perfect honour, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble ſeruaunt,</hi> Ralph Newberrie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13420:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13420:6"/>
            <head>To the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all actions (Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) in generall, depend vpon their ſpeciall occaſions: ſo the publiſhing of this preſet boke or manuell, proceedeth from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſeuerall reaſons. The firſt, from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll affection and louing kindneſſe, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ildren are bound in conſcience to ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir tender parents, wherewith I, among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther aboue the rest, feele my ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dly touched towards my good and louing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er: whome, as in his life time obedient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euerenced: ſo nowe alſo, after his death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unerall, I am no leſſe carefull to haue remembred: and therefore vnder his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, haue cauſed to be ſet foorth this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Chriſtian exerciſe of his own tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the comfort of all faithfull people, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onument of maintenance in his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The ſecond, from Christian loue and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritie, the bond of all perfection, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſouldiers of Christe are ſpecially <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rged: which then (indeede) moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appeareth, when we, (perceiuing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb facs="tcp:13420:7"/> of our brethren and ſisters ſo infeebled and conſumed with ſickneſſe, or otherwiſe by lawe, through deſert of death, iudged and condemned, that they are past all temporall recouerie,) ſuccour neuertheleſſe their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate ſoules, with comfortable restori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſpirite, that they may the more willingly forſake the wilderneſſe of this worlde, and constantly trauell the high way to heauen. The third, from a godly deſire, to haue other ſemblably occupied, in bestowing (I meane) ſuch their talents, as GOD (the riche and gratious giuer of all good thinges) hath committed and put vnder their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite: that in ſo labouring, they in their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian calling may feele their conſciences diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, the members of Christ his mystical body benefited, and finally, almightie GOD our Creatour glorified. To whom, with the Sonne, and the holie Ghost, be all honor, power, maiestie, and dominion, for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in Chriſt,</hi> Marie Frenche.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13420:7"/>
            <head>To his worſhipfull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell learned brother in lawe, <hi>Adolph Baunweyler, grace and peace through Christ.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Irach in his writing, the ſeuenth Chapter, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs, that we ſhould willingly viſite the ſick. And our ſauiour Chriſt, Matth. 25. will at the laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> accept and take this woorke of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, to viſite the ſicke, euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough it were done to him ſelfe. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Lord Chriſt him ſelf ſaith) <hi>What ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you haue done to any amongſt theſe my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lleſt brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that haue you don vnto me.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as much then, welbeloued brother, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this worke to viſite the ſick, is ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighe and ſpeciall worke of charitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a one, as Chriſt at Doomes day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> allowe and thereby acknowledge vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his diſciples: therefore it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vs, not alonly with our whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtes delight to ſhewe it, but alſo to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e diligent care, howe and after what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, we may properly and rightly viſite
<pb facs="tcp:13420:8"/> the ſicke. And that is ſpecially done in two manner of wayes. For euery ſicke body hath ſpecially neede of two maner of remedies. Firſt, that his ſoul be holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for if the ſoule be once holpen, then will the body be eaſily holpen afterward. Therfore, firſt to remedie the ſoule, is to exhort the ſicke body to repentance, &amp; make him to vnderſtand his ſinne, teach him to call to God for helpe, and after that againe, to comfort and lift vp his fearefull conſcience, and ſet foorth and paint vnto the ſicke body liuely Chriſt, (which is the throne of grace) whereof we haue a fine example of king Ezekia, there did the Prophete Eſaias vſe this maner &amp; order with the ſick king: war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him firſt to repentance, layd before him Gods iudgement, 2. Paral. 32. And as ſoone as he had humbled the king, &amp; called to God for grace, the Prophete then comforted him, and after that, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied his bodily ſickneſſe. 4 Reg. 20. and Eſaias. 38. Sirach alſo putteth vs in minde of like order, in his 38. Chapter. ſpecially, that we in our ſickneſſe ſhuld confeſſe our ſinnes, and amend, then to
<pb facs="tcp:13420:8"/> call to GOD for grace and helpe, after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to take phyſicke. Seeing then that viſitation of the ſicke, is to bee prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> after two manners, as is aboueſaid: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore haue I taken vppon mee to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the firſt way, after the order of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ptures: but not for the learned, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neede it not, but for the wel diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that they might haue ſome ſmal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and one Chriſtian to viſite and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> an other, as much as is neceſſarie to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion. The other way to viſite the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as touching the body, is done in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y wayes, ſpecially with attending <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n them, giuing them meat &amp; drink, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng them vp, &amp; laying them downe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſelling them wherein they neede, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n other like helpings, exerciſes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs: theſe wayes can euery man after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſort doe, if he be diſpoſed after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of charitie, to deale with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: and therefore here not neceſſarie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y much more, although that I before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> time, in my booke of Gods wrath, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſufficiently ſhewed, how one ſhuld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fort the ſicke: Yet I haue thought it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d at this time, to ſet foorth a little
<pb facs="tcp:13420:9"/> forme very ſhort, &amp; alſo declare briefly certeine warnings &amp; comforts, after di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſorts: out of which euery man may take one, two, or moe comfortes, to be made vnto the ſicke, as a man thinketh good, or as his ſpirit ſhal moue him, and as he for the time ſhall thinke neceſſarie for the ſicke perſon. For one ſicke body is farre vnlike an other, ſome haue more te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other, one hath ben be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand beter inſtructed in gods word then an other: therefore no man ſhal be bound to bring out al that is herein wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. And welbeloued brother in lawe, I haue thought good to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend this litle comfortable booke vnto you, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that you, &amp; other good folk, as time and oportunitie ſhall ſerue, may vſe it as neceſsitie ſhall require: and you ſhall ſee it good chiefly therfore, bicauſe you hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto with great diligence and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, haue taken vpon you to ſtudie the ſcriptures. Our Lorde God graunt you his grace, that ye may vſe the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to his prayſe, and to the profite and commoditie of your neighbors. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gaspar Huberine.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13420:9"/>
            <head>Howe ſicke folke are to be viſited, perſuaded, admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, <hi>and comforted.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt welbeloued,</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God hath ſent you this ſickneſſe, al for the beſt, (as without dout will ſoone appeare) for, <hi>To the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>things must ſerue to the best.</hi> As Saint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aule witneſſeth in his. <hi>8.</hi> Chapter to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Romanes. Therefore be not afraid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Lord God is ſo good, that he can, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d will turne all troubles and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies which happen or come to his elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to the beſt purpoſe.</p>
            <q>What is to be ſaide to them that be about ſicke folke.</q>
            <p>Secondly, welbeloued in the Lorde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he holy Apoſtle Saint Paul in the <hi>12.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hapter to the Romanes warneth vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at we ſhoulde wéepe with them that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lepe.<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.</note> And Syrach alſo remembreth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his <hi>7.</hi> Chapter, where he ſaith, <hi>Be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:13420:10"/> with them that be ſorrowfull.</hi> For as much then as we in the Lord Chriſt be all members amongſt our ſelues, each one to other, it is méet, that euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, according to his proprietie, nature, ſkill, and abilitie, with comfort make haſt and repaire vnto the ſicke, féeble, ſicke, and diſeaſed member. Therefore ſhall we as it were ſuffer, take, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and be troubled with this ſicke bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and each of vs with all diligence and carefulneſſe and earneſtneſſe, of heartie loue looke vnto, and attend vppon it: be carefull for it, pray to GOD for it, and (to be ſhort) helpe and comfort it the beſt we can, euen as euery of vs woulde, (if we were ſicke,) require of other.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, welbeloued, ye ſhal marke and conſider, that all things come from God, whether they be ſickneſſe, pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, aduerſitie, as witneſſeth Syrache in his <hi>11.</hi> Chapter, where he ſaith thus, <hi>All things come from GOD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le. 11.</note> 
               <hi>aduerſitie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, life and death, pouertie and riches.</hi> And further, holy Saint Paule in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13420:10"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians, and <hi>11.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> Chapter, ſaith, <hi>When we are iudged, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we corrected by the Lord.</hi> He ſaith, By the Lord, (not by an euill man, or by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uel,) but by the Lord him ſelfe are we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rrected. Therefore, <hi>If we liue, we liue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Lorde: If we dye, we dye to the Lorde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore whether we liue or dye we be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordes.</hi> As Saint Paule ſaith in the <hi>12.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Romanes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, you ſhall further earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> marke, vnderſtand, and knowe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot only al puniſhments and ſufferings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me from God, and be layde vppon vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y God: but ye ſhall alſo earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eue, that GOD fendeth vnto his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en, as a very merciful father, ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſhmentes and ſufferings of méere fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our and grace (to his owne) for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ofite and commoditie.</p>
            <p>For there be two cauſes, why God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ndeth vnto vs aduerſities, troubles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d paſſions, ſéeing that God hath two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tes of children vpon the earth.</p>
            <p>Some many times lead a long time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnrepentaunt life, they cannot not
<pb facs="tcp:13420:11"/> abide that a man of loue and good will ſay any thing vnto them, but continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally runne foreward in their miſchief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, frowarde, and naughtie wayes. They haue GOD very little before their eyes. Therfore muſt God lay hold on them, reſtraine &amp; draw them backe, and to true repentaunce and godly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing driue and inforce them, or els they will dye in their wicked &amp; froward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. Therfore doth God lay in the necke of backſliders from him, ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, that they may looke well about them, and marke well who is at their backes, and layeth ſuch a yoke on their neckes, at the laſt to knowe themſelues, and learne what they be, whereabout they goe, and howe they againſt GOD haue ſo grieuouſly offended. Thus God correcteth them through puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and learneth them (as the Prophet Eſaias ſaith in the <hi>28.</hi> Chap.) that doth the ſoule very much good,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tie. 28.</note> and ſuche aduerſitie is a precious medicine, for trouble onely maketh a man take héede to the word. Eſaias <hi>28. <hi>Then doeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13420:11"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e worde of God very well ſauour vnto vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en it is pouldred, mingled, or ſawced with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ubles and paſſions. For when trouble is at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de, then we ſeeke to God, and when God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h viſite vs, then we call earnestly.</hi>
               </hi> Eſai.<note place="margin">Eſai. 26.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Therefore doeth God many times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mplaine againſt his fooliſh ignoraunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople, Eſaias. <hi>9.</hi> where God ſaith,<note place="margin">Eſaie. 9.</note> 
               <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ople do not turne backe to them that haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icken them, nor inquireth after the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of Sabbaoth.</hi> Which is a great token <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an vnrepentant and ſtubberne heart. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſides that, it is a great and heauie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne againſt the Lord God: from whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e God mercifully defend vs. Amen. The other cauſe wherfore our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d layeth troubles and aduerſities vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his children, is this ſpecially, bicauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Lord God will leade his choſen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en from faith to faith, and continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> maketh them expert and cunning in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e knowledge of God, and will thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue them in faith and godly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge, whereby his name by this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s may be the better knowne, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, &amp; prayſed, as we ſée in good Dauid,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:12"/> Ionas, and Iob, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, ſéeing that ye perceiue and knowe that ye are fleſh, &amp; fleſhly weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hath many times preuailed, and you had the vpper hande vpon you, and you haue oftentimes giuen ouer your ſelfe to your olde Adam, and followed fleſhe and bloud too muche, and thereby many times diſpleaſed our Lord God. Thus ſhall you therefore before the high ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of GOD, humble your ſelfe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your offences, aſke mercy, haue a ſeuere purpoſe to abſteine from ſinne, and (if God will againe reſtore you) to liue in a good, perfect, Chriſtian, penitent life, to embrace Gods mercy in Chriſt our deliuerer, &amp; ſtay and holde your ſelfe, with an holie hope vpon his comfortable promiſes. Therefore thus ſay earneſtly after me with heart and minde.</p>
            <p>ALmightie, euerlaſting, &amp; moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God &amp; Father, I acknowledge from the bottome of my heart, and ſay with my mouth, that I am a poore and damnable ſinner. For I am in ſin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13420:12"/> &amp; borne. Beſides that, from my youth hitherto, all the imaginations &amp; thoughtes of my heart haue bene very wicked, and inclined to al ſinne and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe. There is alſo no true feare of God, no faithful loue of God, no perfect faith of God in my heart hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, (oh Lord) founden. Alſo I haue with my mouth (oh God) little called vppon God my lord, &amp; in my trouble fled vnto him for ſuccour. I haue alſo bene very vnthankfull to God my Lord, for all his wonderfull benefites, both bodily and ghoſtly. Likewiſe alſo haue I litle pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or ſet foreward the thankes due to God, and the ſame acknowledged &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed: much leſſe haue I rightly ben de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſet forward, &amp; maintein Gods true ſeruice. To be ſhort, I haue not in my whole life time done and brought forth any good thing, wherby before god I haue brought foorth any godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, to his glory, honour, and praiſe, wherevnto he hath chiefly created and made me. Al this I confeſſe, and it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me from the bottome of my heart,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:13"/> that I haue ſo grieuouſly offended thée, my very God, Lord, &amp; father, eſpecially with euill thoughts, words, and déedes.</p>
            <p>Againe, I acknowledge and confeſſe thée my Lord and God, that I haue not rightly and truly obeied them, to whom I ought obedience. Alſo I haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times grieuouſly offended my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and not ſufficiently ſhewed vnto them Chriſtian charitie and loue: but haue bene many times diſdainefull, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, fierce, and very ſowre. Alſo I haue bene many times kindled in euil luſtes and deſires, in forbidden loue. Alſo I haue bene many times ouerſéene with lewd thoughts. I haue alſo many times ben too ſtreight to my neighbours, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, not holpen them, defended them, nor comforted them. I haue like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe offended and hurt my neighbour by word, ſpoken euill behinde his back, and condemned him. To be ſhort, all wicked deſires and luſtes haue taken in me very mightie vpperhand. Therefore I acknowledge this my ſinfull life, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire mercy, haue pitie vpon me Lorde
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13420:13"/> heauenly father, for the bitter paſſion &amp; death of thine onely ſonne our Lorde.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Heare your comfort.</head>
               <p>Thus ſaith Saint Paule in the firſt Epiſtle to Timothie the ſeconde Chap. <hi>There is one God and one mediatour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpecially the man Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte that hath giuen him ſelfe for all, for our deliuerance.</hi> Beléeue this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſaying, holde faſt on Ieſus Chriſt our onely Lord and Sauiour, ſo ſhall you in your conſciences reſt in peace and quietnes with God the Lord. God graunt his grace thervnto, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ But if the ſicke bodie be ſo weake, and cannot make ſuch a long confeſſion, you may vſe an other ſhorter in this maner.</head>
               <head type="sub">An other confeſſion to the Lord God.</head>
               <p>OH thou merciful, gratious, good God and father, I wretched, ſinfull, ſicke, miſerable, forſaken creature, come nowe before thy high and mightie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, as a poore ſinfull creature, full of ſinne and vnrighteouſneſſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb facs="tcp:13420:14"/> vnto thée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my heart, that I haue grieuouſly ſinned againſt thée from my youth hitherto, with wicked thoughtes, words, and déedes. Theſe do I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege and confeſſe altogether generally, for I am not able to remember &amp; num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all at length particularly, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my God, be gratious to me a poore ſinner, through the deſerts of thy louing Son our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which was therfore ſlaine for me wretched ſinner, to the intent that I ſhould be and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine thy childe for euermore. Amen.</p>
               <q>Hearken to this comfort.</q>
               <p>Thus ſaith S. Iohn the holy Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, in his firſt Epiſtle and the thirde Chapter, <hi>The bloud of Ieſus Christe Gods Sonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Iohn. 3</note> 
                  <hi>maketh vs cleane from all ſinne.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue theſe wholſome, comfortable, and gratious wordes, ſtande ſtedfaſtly in a true beléefe, ſo ſhall you be a childe of euerlaſting life. Amen.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, nowe dearely beloued, ſéeing you haue humbled your ſelfe before our Lorde God, confeſſed your ſinnes, and haue cryed for grace and mercy, ye ſhal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13420:14"/> nowe call vnto our Lord God, from all your heart, firſt and chiefly ſéeke for helpe, and ſay thus.</p>
               <p>OH thou mercifull good God &amp; father, I come now to thée in my great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, and cry vnto thée, and complain from the bottome of my heart, as to my louing father, my greuous paſſions and griefes, and exhort thée that thou wilt remember thy comfortable promiſes, for thou haſt gratiouſly promiſed that I ſhal be heard, where thou in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 50.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50</note> Pſal. ſaieſt, <hi>Cal vpon me in thy neceſſitie or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and I wil heare thee, &amp; thou ſhalt praiſe me.</hi> And Saint Marke in the 11.<note place="margin">Mark. 11</note> Chapter ſaith, <hi>What ſo euer you aske in your prayers, onely beleeue that you ſhall receiue it, and ſo ſhall you haue it.</hi> Vnto theſe thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes come I forſaken, miſerable wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and craue of thée helpe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, therefore my chiefly beloued Lord and father, help me out of this my griefe and trouble, and forſake me not in any of my tormentes, for thine onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake. Therfore ſhall I alwayes highly laud &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13420:15"/> praiſe thy name, &amp; giue thée thanks fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottom of my hart for al thy benefits, &amp; ſet foorth &amp; number the ſame always.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, nowe deare friend, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that your offences commited might make you afraide, and weaken your faith, that ye dare not with all confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and ſure truſt require at Gods hand, and hope for helpe and grace, and truſt ſurely vppon his mercie, you ſhall in this manner call vppon God for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of your ſinnes, and ſpeake thus.</p>
               <p>Oh thou moſt deare Lorde, and very louing God, ſéeing thou haſt made vs ſo many and great promiſes, whereby we might be richly comforted &amp; ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all our troubles and aduerſities, I am bolde to put thée in remembraunce once againe very earneſtly of thy true promiſes, whiche thou haſt made vnto me, in the 6. of Saint Matthewe, where thou haſt promiſed me forgiueneſſe of all my ſinnes, if I do forgiue my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours that wherein they haue offended againſt me.<note place="margin">Matt. 6.</note> For theſe be thy wordes, <hi>If you forgiue other their faults, ſo wil alſo your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13420:15"/> heauenly father forgiue you your offences.</hi> Therefore come I vnto thée, and ſtay me vpon thy worde, ſpecially that thou wilt forgiue me all my ſinns, according to thy mercifull promiſe, fréely, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſo that I alſo doe forgiue other. For theſe nowe I praye vnto thée my Lord and God, that thou wilt ſend into my heart thy holy ſpirite for thy bitter paſſion &amp; death ſake, that he may make cleane my ſinfull hart, lighten and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a feruent heate in me, that I alſo may forget and forgiue. For (of myne own power) I can do nothing, &amp; ſo from the bottome of my heart ſhall I forgiue euery man, both my friendes and eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, what ſo euer they haue done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and put out of my heart all manner of malice, hatred, enimitie, and diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>And ſéeing that I now, through thy grace, perceiue ſuch loue againſt myne enimie, ſo am I nowe perſuaded, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy promiſes, that thou nowe haſt clearely forgiuen me all my ſinnes, of méere mercy without my deſertes.
<pb facs="tcp:13420:16"/> For there haue I a perfect ſigne &amp; good aſſuraunce, ſéeing I haue (according to thy promiſe) forgiuen euery man, that thou alſo haſt forgiuen me all. Do with me according to thy promiſe, for thy word is true, &amp; whatſoeuer thou ſayeſt, that kéepeſt thou aſſuredly. Vpon this thy word do I ſtay, &amp; without all doubt beléeue I thy promiſe, that I haue now gotten forgiueneſſe of all my ſinnes, wherefore I haue nowe a frée, ſafe, and ioyfull conſcience, that I know not now of any ſin in me, &amp; that I haue obteined from God peace &amp; ioy in the holy ghoſt, that I certeinely perſuade my ſelfe of. Amen. Eightly, now welbeloued, the holy ſcripture ſheweth vs of two gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings of Chriſt our lords body vnto vs. The firſt is the generall giuing, where Chriſt gaue vs wretched ſinners his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, for an offering for our ſinnes, this giuing is made vnto vs our owne through true faith, ſpecially when we ſurely beléeue Gods promiſes. Ioh. 6.<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> Of this giuing witneſſeth Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf. Ioh. 3.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 3.</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>So hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13420:16"/> God loued the world, that he hath giuen his owne ſonne, to the intent that al that beleue on him, ſhuld not be deſtroied, but inioy euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</hi> And further, the holy Apoſtle S. Paule, Rom. 8.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> witneſſeth likewiſe &amp; ſaith, <hi>If God be on our ſide, who can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, whiche hath not ſpared his owne ſonne, but hath giuen him for vs all?</hi> And Rom. 4.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt is for our ſinne ſake giuen, and for our righteouſneſſe ſake raiſed vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi> And to the Ephe. 5.<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> ſaith S. Paul moreouer, <hi>Chriſt hath loued vs, and giuen him ſelfe for vs an oblation &amp; ſacrifice.</hi> Theſe &amp; ſuch like ſayings you ſhal dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently marke, &amp; ſtedfaſtly beléeue, that Chriſt our only ſauiour hath giuen and offred vp his body &amp; bloud vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe for you a ſufficient ſacrifice for euer, &amp; ye ſhal not néed to ſéeke or to hunt after any other ſacrifice, ſatiſfaction, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for your ſin, but lay faſt holde vpon this innocent lambe,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> which hath borne the ſinnes of the whole worlde.</p>
               <p>The other giuing of the body &amp; bloud of our lord Chriſt, is an eſpecial giuing which is deliuered vnto vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb facs="tcp:13420:17"/> Whereof Chriſt ſpeaketh, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe 26.<note place="margin">Math. 26</note> And holy Saint Paule in the 10. &amp; 11.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.11</note> Chapter of his firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians. This ſecond deliuering of the body and bloud of Chriſte, in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, is an aſſuring and an a certey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the eſtabliſhing of the firſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering or giuing. For it confirmeth the firſt giuing, which we receiue by faith. And the ſecond doth not profite or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs, without the firſt, but is rather hurtful and damnable. Therefore war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs alſo the holy Apoſtle S. Paule,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11</note> in the 11. Chap. of his ſaide firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians, that we ſhoulde well try our ſelues, before that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holy ſacrament of Chriſtes body and bloud, that no man receiue them to his condemnation. This proofe ſtandeth vpon thrée points.</p>
               <p>Firſt ye ſhal acknowledge your ſelfe for a miſerable ſinner, that of him ſelfe and by him ſelfe can doe nothing, nor hath any power to do any thing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might be deliuered from his ſinne. God him ſelfe doth forgiue, reconcile,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13420:17"/> and pardon, giueth true comfort, &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth bleſſedneſſe, ſpecially to them that doe thirſt after the grace of GOD. And ſo of méere grace and mercie in Chriſte onely, doe long after the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</p>
               <p>Secondly, examine well your ſelues, whether ye beléeue as Saint Paul ſaith in the 13. Chapter of his ſeconde Epiſtle to the Corinthes,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13</note> 
                  <hi>Try your ſelues</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>whether ye be in belefe, proue your ſelues &amp;c.</hi> Specially y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye earneſtly &amp; ſtedfaſtly beléeue the godly promiſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is promiſed in the Sacrament. Item, wherfore that godly meate is giuen vnto you.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, examine your ſelfe well, whether ye canne and will forgiue your neighbor, whether they be friends or foes that haue offended or hurt you, whereby ye can ſhewe towards al men, a Chriſtian, friendly, louing and courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart, and good will. For this pray vnto our Lord God nowe once againe. And if for your ſickneſſe you can not ſpeake it with your mouth, yet in your heart inwardly ſay thus.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13420:18"/>
               <p>My Lorde Ieſus Chriſte I come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as a wretched ſinner vnto thée, that haue many times offended thée, &amp; haue deſerued nothing but thy euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting diſpleaſure and puniſhment. But ſeeing thou art ſo gentle and mercifull, thou willeſt not the death of a ſinner, but that he repent and liue: therefore haſt thou eſtabliſhed among vs a newe Teſtament, whiche was long before promiſed by thy holy prophetes, that thou wouldeſt take our ſinnes from vs, through thy death, and the ſame neuer after remember. And alſo before thy death haſt made thy laſt will, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in haſt made vs an aſſured promiſe that thou wouldeſt giue vs thy body (for our redemption) to be ſlaine, and ſhed thy bloud for remiſſion of our ſinnes, For thus ſoundeth thy gratious promiſe: <hi>Take, eate, this is my body, which ſhal be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for you. This is the cupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the newe teſtament in my bloud, which ſhalbe ſhed for you, for the forgiueneſſe of your ſinnes.</hi> This thy promiſe doe I beléeue ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly, and for aſſurance thereof, I haue
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13420:18"/> before this time in my good health of body, many times in the congregation of God receiued the holy Sacrament of thy very body and bloud, wherof at this preſent I doe not doubt, but am nowe certeinly and aſſuredly perſuaded of al thy graces and mercies. Be it vnto me according to thy word.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Here it is good to put the ſicke body in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce ſhortly, what hath beene ſaide before, after this manner.</head>
               <p>Ninethly, now deare friends I haue tolde you in the beginning, how that all aduerſities and troubles come from our Lord God, and be laide vpon his (of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly and true loue.) Therefore ſhall you be certeinely perſuaded, that this your ſickneſſe is by God therefore laide vpon you, that the old man with Chriſt ſhoulde be nayled vpon the croſſe, that the ſinfull body ſhoulde ceaſe, and a new and perfecte man appeare thereof, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che with Chriſte ſhall inioy euerlaſting ioy and felicitie: For, <hi>Fleſh and bloud can not enherit the kingdome of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> As ſaint
<pb facs="tcp:13420:19"/> Paule witneſſeth 1. Cor. 15. The olde man muſt full and whole be deſtroyed, and as Chriſte in the 12. Chap. of Saint Iohn ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Except that the wheate corne fall into the earth and die, ſo remaineth it but one corne: But if it die, it bringeth forth much fruite.</hi> Thus muſt all both within and without vs be forſaken, the olde A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam with all his wiſedome, reaſon and vnderſtanding come to nought, wherby a newe man may appeare at that day, as Saint Paule ſaith 1. Cor. 15. Where he ſpeaketh thus:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>That whiche we ſee is not liuely, except it firſt die. It is ſowen in corruption, and ſhall riſe againe in glorie. It is ſowen in diſhonour, and ſhall riſe againe in honour. It was ſowen in weakeneſſe, and ſhall riſe againe in might. It was ſowen a naturall body, and it ſhall riſe againe a ſpirituall body. When this corruptible body hath put on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption, and this mortalitie hath put on immortalitie: then ſhalbe fulfilled the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which is written, Death is ſwalowed vp in victorie, Death where is thy ſting? Hell where is thy victorie? God be praiſed that hath giuen vs the victorie through our Lord
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13420:19"/> Ieſus Chriſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondarily, ſéeing the caſe ſtandeth thus, you ſhall nowe further reſigne and forſake your owne wil, and giue it ouer to Gods wil, and pray as our Lord God hath taught vs to pray Matth. 6.<note place="margin">Matt. 6.</note> and ſay: <hi>Father, thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen.</hi> And as Chriſte Gods ſonne him ſelfe at the houre of his death hath done, and hath ſet forth vnto vs, an example to be followed, where he ſaide vpon mount Oliuet, Matth 26.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Father, not my will, but thy will be done.</hi> So ſhall ye alſo doe vnto him, conforme your ſelfe in all thinges to God him ſelfe our Lord, and giue ouer all thinges to him, our body, our life, our ſoule, our eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our goods, friendes, wife, children, and all, &amp;c. and ſay thus.</p>
               <p>NOw my Lord and God, wil it none otherwiſe be, but that I muſt at this time néedes drinke the cuppe of my paſſion, that thou haſte filled for me to drinke, let thy will be done. As thou willeſt, ſo will I alſo, I am willing and readie, I am thy childe, and thou arte
<pb facs="tcp:13420:20"/> my louing father, thou wilt not deſtroy me, that I knowe right well. Oh one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue thou me grace, ſtrength, power, mercie, patience, to ſuffer all thinges willingly, that I may to thée kéepe a right holy day, continually holde faſt by thée, and willingly to ſuffer thée to doe with me according to thy fatherly good will and pleaſure. Then ſhall I thrée dayes long reſt &amp; lie with Chriſte in the graue, &amp; hope for a ioyfull reſurrection of all beléeuers at domes day, according to the comfortable promiſe of Chriſte, Iohn the 6.<note place="margin">Iohn. 6</note> where Chriſte ſaith thus: <hi>This is the will of him that ſent me, that he that ſeeth the ſonne and beleeueth on him, haue euerlaſting life, and I will raiſe him vp at the latter day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, ye ſhall alſo further vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande and beléeue certeinely, that this your ſickneſſe, howe great, howe ſore, howe gréeuous to ſuffer, howe long and painefull ſoeuer it bée, yet is it not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to appeaſe &amp; pacifie Gods wrath, to take away your ſinnes, and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe you euerlaſting life. For ye ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13420:20"/> ſtedfaſtly beléeue this, that deſeruing of any Saint, nor your owne worke, how precious ſo euer it bée, or may bée, can gett you heauen, or can deſerue it. For Saint Paule ſaith Rom. 8.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> That <hi>All the ſufferinges in this worlde be not worthie of that glorie that ſhalbe ſhewed vnto vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, ye ſhall vndoubtedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, that the onely paſſion and death of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, is a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent oblation for your ſinnes. For, <hi>The Lorde Ieſus is made for vs from God, to be our wiſedome, our righteouſneſſe, our ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and deliuerer,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaint Paul witneſſeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians the firſt Chapter.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>For there is none other name giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to men, nor there is in none other helth wherin we ſhalbe ſaued, then on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the name of Ieſus Chriſte, &amp;c.</hi> As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe witneſſeth Saint Peter Acts the fourth,<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>For God hath made him that neuer knewe ſinne, for our ſakes to be ſinne, to the intent that we ſhoulde be made in him righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, auayleable before him.</hi> 2. Cor. 5.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore we nowe beleeue</hi> (ſaith Saint Paule further,) Rom. 3. <hi>that man is
<pb facs="tcp:13420:21"/> made righteouſneſſe without the workes of the lawe, onely through faith,</hi> As Saint Peter alſo ſaith in the tenth Chapter of the Actes.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctes. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Of Chriſte</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>witneſſe all the Prophets, that through his name al that beleeue in him, ſhall haue forgiueneſſe of their ſinns. For Chriſt</hi> (ſaith S. Peter fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) 1. Pet. 2.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>hath offered vp our ſinnes on his body vpon the croſſe, that we being dead to ſinne, might liue to righteouſnes, by whoſe wounds ye are made whole.</hi> Such and like ſayings is the holy Scripture very ful, that altogether witneſſeth that we be made iuſt, righteous, and ſanctified through faith in Ieſus Chriſt, without any our owne doinges. For Chriſte is the only ranſome for our ſinnes, for we be bought through the precious bloud of Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, ye ſhall nowe forgiue euery man willingly from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottome of your heart, forget, and forgiue what ſo euer hath béene done againſt vs, whether ye knowe it, or knowe it not, whether it be with worde or déede, by any meanes done againſt you: for ſéeing that our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13420:21"/> Lorde God of méere grace hath caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, and forgiuen you ſo many ſinnes, which you haue ſo many times committed againſt him, from your child<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hoode till this time, ſmall and great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which many &amp; oftentimes ye haue committed all the dayes of your life, ſo that if God ſhould reckon all your olde ſinnes, and deale with you after his ſtrong iudgement, aſke ſatiſfaction, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thoſe offences, he might gréeuouſly viſite you as a righteous God: and yet doth he not ſo, nor neuer hereafter will doe, but as a mercifull father, of ſpeciall grace forgetteth and forgiueth all, and the ſame will neuer more thinke vpon, nor reckon, but couer them, and ſcrape them out.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe doeth he alſo require for thankes, laude, and prayſe, none other thing, but ye forgiue and forget your neighbours, what ſo euer they haue at any time offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded againſt you. And you ſhal not only your offenders gladly and heartily forgiue: but alſo againe, ſhewe your ſelfe againſt them thankfull. And
<pb facs="tcp:13420:22"/> for the poore widowes and fatherleſſe children, according to your abilitie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide ſomething, whereby they may be fed, clothed, and mainteined, ſo ſhal they at the laſt day be your witneſſes, that your faith was a perfect faith, ſéeing it is liuely by workes,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ala. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pet. 1.</note> Gala. 6. <hi>Make your election ſure,</hi> through ſuch works of loue, as Saint Peter ſaith. 2. Pet. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ If the ſicke body be any thing rich, then a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy may bee the more earneſt and diligent, to exhort them to almes giuing: but ſo, that the ſicke perſon be not perſuaded to put truſt in his owne workes, and bring him into a vaine hope, that he ſhal purchaſe heauen by his almes. Therefore conſideration muſt be had to the ſoule, that it be not lead out of the right way, into the way that is full of briers and thornes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Howe they that ſtand by, are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to pray for the ſicke.</head>
               <p>Tenthly, beloued in Chriſt our Lorde, ſéeing we be at this preſent here ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, I put you in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye will be mindfull of our true &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13420:22"/> Chriſtian duetie, that we are bound one to an other as members of Chriſte, that ye will diligently and earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the griefes and ſickneſſes of this our friend, and not onely haue an earneſt compaſſion vppon him, but alſo earneſtly and truely pray to our Lorde God for him, that our Lord God will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his owne ſonne, in whom he doth much delight, that he will mitigate and ſhorten the great ſickneſſe, paines, and paſſions of this our ſicke friende, and graunt vnto him a true Chriſtian pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that with all confidence, he may wholy put his affiaunce and comfort in Gods mercy, and continually vnto the end ſtedfaſtly abide in true faith vppon Chriſte our deliuerer, and in thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that apperteine to our bleſſed hope, to remaine and abide willingly, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently take and beare ſuche his croſſe layde vpon him, vntill our Lord God of his mercy do viſit him, and deliuer him, and bring him at his appointed time out of this trouble and miſerie, to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioy and felicitie. Séeing then
<pb facs="tcp:13420:23"/> that our Lord Chriſt hath promiſed vs, then we be gathered together in his name, he will gratiouſly heare vs, and graunt thoſe thinges that we deſire. Now let vs call vpon almightie God in true faith, and pray, in the name of Chriſt our Lord, ſo will he certeinly at the laſt heare vs, according to his father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will &amp; good pleaſure, therefore make your prayer to GOD our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſay, <hi>Our father, &amp;c.</hi> Almightie GOD, vouchſafe mercifully to graunt our prayer, through Chriſte our Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ If the ſickneſſe do linger and driue off, ſo that the patient be aſſaulted with grieuous ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then may a body ſometime ſhewe him of theſe comforts following, and alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare one comfort or two. For like as a body muſt nowe and then releeue the ſicke body, with comfortable medicines, and brothes: likewiſe ſhal now and then releeue and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſoule, whereby the ſoule may haue her ſuſtenaunce. And yet we ſhall not be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to the ſicke, and make him haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, or be offended in his head, and euer to haue regard, whether he be troubled with any temptation, and whether he haue a deſire and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13420:23"/> luſt to heare Gods word: for the ſicke muſt haue his eaſe and quietneſſe. So that with too much reading and crying vpon him, ye bring him into raging, or paſſions, and make his head ydle, feeble, and weake. Herein ought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery body to vſe diſcretion, and put diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</head>
               <p>FFirſt welbeloued in Chriſte, let not any tentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make you faint harted: for Chriſte is a valiant &amp; mightie king, ouer death, ſinne, and all aduerſitie. Therefore abide vpon this ſtone, which is Ieſus Chriſt, ſtande faſt, and ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not the gates of hell preuaile againſt you. Then this Lord and King is gone before you vnto death, he hath trode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pathe, and made the way, and alſo hath ouerthrown death, &amp; taken his ſtrength from him: ſo that death cannot hurt you, hinder you, nor kéepe you backe. Therefore be not diſmayed euen in the middeſt of death, and thinke thus. In the name of God, Gods will be don. All this geare will be gone within a twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye. Then ſhall I paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the ſnares of death. Then haue I throwen at my backe all miſfortune,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:24"/> feare, and deſperation. For this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent death is vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful a ſafe port, through which I ſhall goe into heauen. Then muſte ſinne, death, hell, paines, paſſions, hunger, thirſt, froſt, trouble, and all aduerſitie together ceaſſe and leaue-off. Therefore be not diſmaied, for if GOD be with you, who ſhalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you? Say, avaunt and fare well nowe the whole worlde, and alſo the Prince of this worlde, whiche woulde hinder you the way to euerlaſting life: for as much as Chriſte is your Iuſtice, your Loadeſman and your Guide.</p>
               <p>Secondely, well be loued, if Gods wrath, threatening, and puniſhment, ſhoulde feare you, diſmay you, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your mind, as though our Lord God as an earneſt and ſeuere Iudge, ſhould deale with you according to his extreme iuſtice for your ſinnes paſt, then ſhall you from henceforth call vpon our Lord Chriſte, the vnſpotted Lamb of GOD, whiche hath taken your ſinnes vppon him, and thus flée from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of Gods iuſtice, &amp; commit your ſelfe to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13420:24"/> ſeate of Chriſte our Lorde. For ye haue a ſpeciall and faithfull promiſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte: for he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed and giuen him ſelfe for wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſinners, and ſo bound and pledged him ſelfe for all penitent ſinners, that he will ſtand to them, and deliuer them from Gods wrath. Alſo Saint Paule witneſſeth 1. Theſ. 1.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath our Lorde Ieſus</hi> (ſaith the holy Apoſtle) <hi>raiſed vp from death, that hath deliuered vs from the wrath to come.</hi> And 1. Theſ. 5.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.</note> ſaith Saint Paule further, <hi>God hath not appointed vs to inherit his wrath, but to inherit his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe, through our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, whiche died for vs.</hi> Marke and conſider this diligently.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, welbeloued, if the worlde do trouble you, and though ſome folkes, ſpecially your enimies and euil willers reioyce and be glad that you (according to their deſires) be ſo gréeuouſly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and that you be now by God ſo fore puniſhed, and that they therfore mocke, ſcorne, deſpiſe you, and make greate cheare at your trouble: yet let not that
<pb facs="tcp:13420:25"/> trouble nor tempt you: for ſéeing that wicked people mocked Chriſte at the houre of his death, and made great cheare at it: likewiſe ſhall you of the worlde not eſcape ſuch thinges. Séeing you be a member of Chriſte, you muſte ſuffer in your body, all ſuch troubles as wanted in Chriſtes paſſion, as Saint Paule ſaith,<note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> the firſt Chap. to the Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians. Therefore is the worlde a ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, proud, and wicked child of ſathan whiche is full of all wickedneſſe, diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mockerie, &amp; backbiting. Chriſt for our comforte hath tolde vs before, that we muſte ſuffer and beare many thinges of the worlde, and that the worlde ſhoulde laugh vs to ſcorne, and ſhoulde reioyce at our trouble: and we on the other ſide, a little while ſhuld be penſiue and ſorrowfull. But Chriſt comforteth vs and ſaith, <hi>Your ſorrow ſhal be turned into ioy.</hi> Iohn 6.<note place="margin">Iohn. 6</note> And Iohn, 17.<note place="margin">Iohn. 17</note> 
                  <hi>In the world you ſhall haue ſorrowe &amp; care: but comfort your ſelfe, I haue ouercome the worlde.</hi> Thus ſhall you in faith beare all the wickedneſſe of the world, ſuffer,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13420:25"/> and ouercome. For, <hi>Our faith is the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie that hath ouercome the worlde,</hi> Iohn. 15.<note place="margin">Iohn. 15</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, moreouer dearely beloued, if Moſes the lawegiuer ſet vppon you, and will make you afraid with his debt booke, and put you out of countenaunce for your great debtes &amp; notable ſinnes, whiche you are bounde to ſatiſfie and pay the terrible iudgement of God, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye are a breaker or tranſgreſſor of gods lawes, and therfore, will call you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, and giue euidence againſt you, and condemne you with your own hand writing &amp; your own conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (knowing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to be true) complaine vpon you, and accuſeth you: then ſhall you before Moſes by and by bring forth your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie, wherby Chriſt hath made you frée, and deliuered you from the lawe, and from the curſe and maledic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. For, <hi>If Gods ſonne haue made you free, then be you free in deede,</hi> Iohn. 8.<note place="margin">Iohn. 8</note> And as Saint Paul further doth ſhew and confirme ſuch fréedome, Galat. 3.<note place="margin">Galat. 3</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>Chriſte hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:13420:26"/> vs from the curſe of the lawe, when he was made a curſe for vs.</hi> Thus can the curſe neuer more ouerrunne nor trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you, ſéeing it hath once all together fallen vppon Chriſte the moſt innocent Lambe. Therefore, ſéeing <hi>Chriſte is the ende of the lawe, whoſoeuer beleeueth on him is made righteous,</hi> Rom. 10.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. 10.</note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith Saint Peter, <hi>Be you luſtie and ſtrong.</hi> Actes, 15.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctes. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e are nowe taught, that forgiueneſſe of ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es commeth by this man, and of all them whereof ye could not be made righteous in the lawe of Moſes.</hi> Who ſo euer beleueth on Chriſt, is righteous. Here is nowe onely all ſinnes taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. So that no man can, or dare, lay any thing to the charge of the faithfull, neither Moſes nor the lawe. Therfore be of good comfort.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, furthermore dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I doe aduiſe you, that you will not ſuffer the great weight and burden of your ſinnes to preſſe, and weigh you downe, and trouble you. For ſinne, I aſſure you, is an heauie burden, to a fearefull conſcience. Wherefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13420:26"/> caſt your ſinnes from you, and out of your conſciences, and caſte them vppon Chriſt, for he is the right carrier of our ſinnes as holy Saint Iohn wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, Iohn. 1.<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note> where he ſaith, Behold, this is the Lambe of God that beareth or carrieth away the ſinns of the world. Therefore let the Lorde and valiaunt Champion take vppe your ſinnes, and carrie them vppon him ſelfe. For God hath appointed him thereunto, as Saint Paule ſaith, where he ſaith thus, GOD hath appointed him (namely Chriſt) that neuer knewe ſinne, to be ſinne it ſelfe for our ſakes: to the intent that we ſhoulde be by him that righteouſneſſe, that is auayleable before God. Behold, this righteous and innocent Lord hath taken all your ſinnes vppon him ſelfe, borne them, ſatiſfied for them, and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed them, and hath clothed you, deck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and trimmed you, with his innocent righteouſneſſe and iuſtice: For, <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſaith the Prophete Eſaie. 53.<note place="margin">Eſaie. 53.</note>) <hi>is for our ſinns wounded, and for our ſinnes beaten and ſmitten. Correction is laide vppon him, to
<pb facs="tcp:13420:27"/> the intent that we ſhould haue peace, and by his wounds ſhould be healed.</hi> Behold, for Gods ſake, &amp; thinke vpon this w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence erneſtly. Chriſt (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet) is wounded for our ſinnes, whereby we might be made whole. The wrath &amp; the correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is cleane gone ouer him, to the intent that we ſhould be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; might inioy peace with GOD. So haue you deliueraunce in Chriſte by his bloud, namely forgiuenes of your ſinnes according to the richneſſe of his grace, Ephe. 1.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>he. 1</note> For, <hi>Chriſte is therefore come into this worlde, to make ſinners holy &amp; bleſſed.</hi> 1. Tim. 1.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im. 1</note> As Chriſt witneſſeth of him ſelfe, Matth. 18.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tt. 18.</note> And Luke. 19.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>k. 19</note> 
                  <hi>The ſonne of man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is come to ſeeke and to make bleſſed that that is loſt. For God hath not ſent his ſonne into the worlde, that he ſhould condemne the world, but that the world by him ſhold be made hapie, whoſoeuer beleeueth on him ſhall not be iudged,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 4</note> Alſo, <hi>Chriſte is the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes.</hi> Beléeue this comfortable ſaying, from the bottome of your heart, and ſtay your ſelfe more vppon Gods mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13420:27"/> then of the deceites of ſathan, and of the daungerous imaginations of your reaſon. Giue God the honour, bicauſe he is ſo merciful a God, that of a wretched ſinner he will make a child of God, if a man will only truſt vpon him.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, moreouer welbeloued, though nowe death at the laſt will come and ſtare in your face, and ſhould with his greuous countenance make you afraid: for he is ſuch a capteine and giant, that he will make one beléeue, he will eate vp the whole world, and therfore he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth ſo wide: yet be not afraide of him, for he aduaunceth him ſelfe maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, and is ougly to behold: howbeit, he hath no power nor ſtrength anye more, to ouerthrowe you. For Chriſte hath matched him, &amp; throughly woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, ſéeing that he hath layd hande vpon Chriſt the right Lion, therefore is all his ſtrength taken from him. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhall be to the faithfull no more death, but only a ſléepe, as Saint Paul in the ſecond Epiſtle to Timothie,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.</note> the firſt Chapter, doth witneſſe and declare
<pb facs="tcp:13420:28"/> very plainly and comfortably, where he ſaith, <hi>Christe Ieſus our ſauiour hath taken the ſtrength from death, and brought vs the light, life, and a being, by meanes of the Gospell, that ſhall neuer corrupt nor periſh.</hi> Yea, the faythfull ſhall neuer taſte of death, as Chriſte witneſſeth him ſelfe, being the very trueth, Iohn the eight Chapter, where he ſaith thus, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily verily I tell you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hn. 8</note> 
                  <hi>if any man will keepe my word (by faith) he ſhall not taste of death e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlastingly.</hi> Looke and marke well what a noble, vertuous, and right beléefe is, for that ouercommeth and driueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all aduerſitie, all plagues, ſinne, &amp; death it ſelfe. And a faithfull perſon go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth cleane through death, to the right life, as our Lord Chriſt againe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, Iohn 5.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hn. 5</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily verily I ſay vnto you, he that heareth my worde, and beleeueth on him that hath ſent me, he hath euerlasting life, and ſhall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into iudgement, but he paſſeth through death to life.</hi> There doe you ſée what is neceſſarie for you: yea, you ſhall eſcape the iudgement of God, ouercome death,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13420:28"/> and inioy euerlaſting life: namely, to heare Gods word (as Chriſte ſaith) and beléeue the ſame. It requireth no great cunning, wiſedome, ſtrength, might, liueland, and preparation, to ouercome death, but this ouercomming, victorie, or triumphe, is in theſe two pointes, to heare and to beléeue.</p>
               <p>Surely, my thinketh, this is a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous victorie, that a poore, wretched, weake, and ſicke man, that by reaſon of weakeneſſe, can ſcant moue hande nor foote, can ouercome ſo great a giant, as death onely, with a Chriſtianlike hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and a beléeuing heart. But thus can Chriſt auenge him ſelfe vpon ſuche a ſtrong enimie death, that would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue eaten and ſwalowed vp Chriſt, that he hath ſo wonderfully taken away the ſtrength from death, that a poore wretched man may ouercome death, &amp; beſides that, may mocke and laugh him to ſcorne, that is (I thinke) death right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deſpiſe and contemne. But howe commeth that to paſſe, that we ouerrun and wearied by death, ſhall neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:13420:29"/> abide ſtill aliue. That is (as Chriſt him ſelfe ſaith) Iohn 11.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 11.</note> where he ſayth thus, <hi>I am the reſurrection and the life, who ſo euer beleeueth on me, ſhall liue, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſeeme to dye. And whoſoeuer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and beleeueth on me, ſhall neuermore dye.</hi> This is the right and onely cauſe, that the faithfull, yea, in the middeſt of death, imbrace the right life, Chriſt our Lord that giueth againe vnto them life. For, as little nowe can death any more wearie or ouercome our Lord, or holde him in death: ſo little can he either pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or quarell with any faithfull men. For ſeeing that Chriſt, which is the life, doth ſtill liue, and can neuermore be ouercome, ſo may the faithfull neuer abide priſoner in death, but he breaketh out valiantly with Chriſte, and ſingeth the merrie ſong of thankes giuing, and of triumph, <hi>Death is ſwallowed vp in vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie,</hi> for where is thy ſting? Thus ſhal a Chriſtian ſouldier looke death betwéen the browes, and manfully wage battell with him, or elſe woulde death eate vp, and ſwallow the whole world. But
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13420:29"/> if you will with a true faith encounter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith him, then will he quietly let you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lone. Wherevnto Chriſte helpe you, he valiaunt and puiſſaunt king ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eath and life. Amen.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, alſo welbeloued, if the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell the tempter would lay hand vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou, aſſault or make you deſpaire, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough you did belong to his kingdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r were in his claws, thus ſhal you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounter him, ſtande againſt him, beate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, ouercome him, firſt by earneſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rayers and calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God for grace, helpe, and comfort, as our Lord Chriſte admoniſhed his Diſciples, Matth. 26.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>Pray you, least ye fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto temptation.</hi> As alſo our louing Lord Chriſt him ſelfe hath taught vs to pray, Luke. 12.<note place="margin">Luke. 12.</note> Oh Lord and father, leade vs not into temptation, ſpecially when we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re tempted by ſathan, and aſſaulted, that we through thy grace and holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, may withſtande him, and that we may eſchue his perſuaſions and entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to doubt. Therefore thus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him by prayer, for ſathan is falne
<pb facs="tcp:13420:30"/> downe hither to vs ſwiftly and inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, as Chriſte our ſauiour witneſſeth, Luke. 10.<note place="margin">Luk. 10.</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>I ſawe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than fal from heauen like a lightening.</hi> But wherefore? Truely therefore, as Chriſt further teacheth his Apoſtles. Luke. 22.<note place="margin">Luke. 22.</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>Simon, Simon, beholde Sathan hath deſired you, that he might fift you as wheat is ſifted. But I haue prayed for thee, that thy faith ſhall not faile.</hi> Beholde nowe how ſathan prouleth after euery man, he ſpareth no man, he durſt aſſault the beſt and holieſt men, namely, Adam and Eue in Paradiſe, though they were made to the Image of God. Alſo he hath not ſpared Gods own ſonne, but aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and tempted him in the wildernes, ſo hath he alſo deſired to doe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like with the deare Apoſtles, as you heard euen nowe: therefore it is to be feared, he will alſo not ſpare you. Séeing then that is to be feared, and that we knowe his meaning, as Saint Paule ſaith in his ſecond Epiſtle to the Corinthians, the ſecond Chapter, that we ſhuld looke about vs, that we be not deceiued of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13420:30"/> For (ſaith he) <hi>It is not vnknowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o vs, what he purpoſeth and goeth about.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.</note> Therefore haue a good eye vppon this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>armefull and perillous tempter, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riue him away by godly prayers.</p>
               <p>Againe, thus ſhall you deſend &amp; ſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt ſathan, with a ſtedfaſt faith on Chriſt our Lord, chiefly, that Chriſte is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur high Prieſt and King, which hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ercome ſathan, the ſame Lord can for our commoditie deſtroy ſathan, &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome him: therefore ſhall you ſtedfaſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eléeue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt your mightie King can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt &amp; driue away ſathan fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll fantaſies, dreames, toyes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eites. For, <hi>He goeth</hi> (as ſaith Saint Peter. 1. Pet. 5.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note>) <hi>about as a roaring Lion, and ſeeketh whom hee may deuour, whome</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>reſist you, being ſtrong in faith: therefore take the ſhield of faith,</hi> (As Saint Paule further warneth vs,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> where he (in the 6. to the Epheſians) ſaith thus, <hi>Before all things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>take the ſhield of faith, whereby ye may quenche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all the fierie dartes of the wicked.</hi> Therfore beléeue ſtedfaſtly, by this noble counſell
<pb facs="tcp:13420:31"/> of the holy Apoſtle Saint Paule, where be ſpeaketh in the firſt Chapter to the Epheſians, and in the firſt to the Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. Coloſs. 1.</note> in this maner, <hi>God hath deliuered vs from the Prince of darkeneſſe, and hath establiſhed vs in the kingdome of his louing ſonne, of whome we haue our deliueraunce through his bloud, ſpecially the forgiueneſſe of ſinns, acording to the richnes of his grace.</hi> There doe you heare, and muſt with your whole heart beléeue, that our Lord Chriſte hath deliuered you from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of ſathan, ſo that the gates of hell can not preuaile againſt you. Matth. 16.<note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, if ſathan moreouer will encounter with you, then take you the ſword of the holy ghoſt, (which is Gods worde) after the counſell of the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, in the 6. to the Epheſians,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> and ſet vpon him with Gods worde, after the example of Chriſt, Matth. 4.<note place="margin">Matth. 4.</note> Therefore, if he will ſay vnto you this or ſuch like wordes, <hi>The vnrighteous ſhall not inherite the kingdome of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> the ſixt Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is written,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Who ſo euer ſinneth, is of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13420:31"/> the firſt Epiſtle of Saint Iohn, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hird Chapter. Then ſhall you anſwere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im againe with Chriſt, and ſay, <hi>Away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>athan, for it is alſo written, &amp;c.</hi> And alſo,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18. &amp; 33</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>deſire not the death of a ſinner,</hi> (ſaith our Lord God) <hi>but that he amend him ſelfe, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ue.</hi> And Chriſte in the 9. of Matthewe,<note place="margin">Matt. 9. Matt. 18. Luk. 19</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith thus, <hi>I am come to call ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entance.</hi> And Matthewe 18. and Luke 9. <hi>The ſonne of man</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſeeke, and to make bleſſed that that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>st.</hi> Nowe looke ſathan, though I be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>éed a wretched ſinner, yet is not Gods will that I ſhould be for euer condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, but that I ſhould liue. Albeit then that I be a loſt ſhéep, yet will Chriſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh ſhepheard of my ſoule, ſéek me out, and ſaue me, of this I doubt nothing at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll. Therefore avaunt harmefull diuel, thou haſt nothing to do here, ſéeing that Chriſt my Lorde hath clothed and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed me with his innocencie, vertues, &amp; holineſſe: for I haue put on Chriſte my Lorde in my baptiſme. Galathians the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hird Chapter.<note place="margin">Galat. 3</note> I haue put on the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing garment, in which I ſhall appeare
<pb facs="tcp:13420:32"/> before God, and dwell in his kingdome for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
               <p>Beholde, thus ſhall you driue away the wicked flend, and ſtriue and fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him as a Chriſtian Capteine, to the end that ye may atteine at the great day, vnto the euerlaſting crown. Thus wil our Lord God (which is the God of peace,) tread downe ſathan after a litle time vnder your feete,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> as Saint Paule writeth, in the 16. to the Romanes.</p>
               <p>Eightly, if welbeloued, the euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iudgement, hell, and euerlaſting damnation aſſault you, as though you were one that ſhould be damned, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken and loſt, and woulde make hell mouth gape, and open wide vppon you: thus comforte and refreſhe your ſelfe euer and quickly with Gods word, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue and coole your ſelfe with the freſhe water that ſpringeth and floweth out of the treaſure of Gods mercy, againſt ſin and filthy liuing, which water we haue in the Goſpell, where alſo the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Zacharias maketh mention in the 13.<note place="margin">Zach. 13. Eſaie. 55.</note> Chapter, and the Prophete Eſaie in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13420:32"/> 55. Cha. Thus imbrace now with true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable, &amp; pleaſant ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngs &amp; promiſes of God, of euerlaſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fe, whereof this is one, Iohn. 3.<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Lorde Chriſte ſpeaketh thus, <hi>God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th not ſent his ſon into the world, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne the world, but that the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrough him ſhould be ſaued. Whoſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeueth on him, ſhall not be condemned.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em, Iohn. 5.<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily verily I ſay vnto you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt our Lord,) <hi>Whoſoeuer hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth my word, &amp; beleeueth in him that hath ſent me, ſhal neuer enter into condemnation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t he hath a through paſſage from death to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi> Item the third of S. Iohn, <hi>Whoſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eleueth on the Sonne, hath euerlaſting life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> And moreouer he ſaith, <hi>Like as Moſes ſet vp a ſerpent in the wilderneſſe, likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ust the ſonne of man alſo be lifted vp, to the intent, that all they that beleeue in him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hould not be loſt and periſh, but inioy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erite euerlasting life.</hi> And, <hi>God hath ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d the world,</hi> (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſting ſonne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God him ſelfe,) <hi>that he hath giuen his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſonne, to the intent that all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeue in him, ſhoulde not be destroyed, but
<pb facs="tcp:13420:33"/> ſhould inioy euerlasting life.</hi> Item, Iohn the ſixte (thus ſaith Chriſte,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6</note>) <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily verily I ſay vnto you, he that beleeueth on me, hath euerlasting life.</hi> Item (our Lorde Chriſte ſaith further thus,) <hi>This is the will of him that ſent me, that whoſoeuer beholdeth the ſonne, and beleeueth on him, ſhal haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life, and I will raiſe him vp at the last day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this may you ioyfully ſay, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and through true faith acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that hel (through the reſurrection of Chriſte our deliuerer) is ſhut vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, for you beléeue the higheſt article of Chriſtian religion, where we beléeue and acknowledge, that Chriſte our Lorde is gone downe into hell, not for his owne ſinne and vnrighteouſnes ſake, but for the cauſe of our wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by whiche we haue deſerued the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting plagues, hell, and damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There hath Chriſt himſelfe taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that euerlaſting correction, done penaunce for it, and made ſatiſfaction, broken hell, and ſhut and ſtopped it vp, and to be ſhort, in ſtead of euerlaſting
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13420:33"/> impriſonment, dungeon, and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, purchaſed and giuen vs euerlaſting life, and brought vnto vs, and giuen vs a triumphant victorie, that we with him may nowe merily ſing, <hi>Hell, where is thy victorie?</hi> Beholde, it behoueth you in ſuch ſore dangerous, and linger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſickneſſe and battel, to ſhew and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct your ſelfe that you be a childe of God, and ſuffer not your ſelfe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, albeit it doeth not as yet appeare in this world, nor can eaſily be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued whether we be preſently through faith fully Gods children or not.<note place="margin">Iohn 1.</note> Iohn the firſt ſaith. <hi>It doeth not yet nowe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare what we be, but we knowe, that when it ſhal appeare, then ſhal we be like vnto him,</hi> The firſt of Saint Iohn the third.<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.3.</note> Cap. <hi>Then ſhall we ſee him as he is, and then ſhal we be pertakers of his Godly nature.</hi> The ſeconde Epiſtle of Saint Peter the firſt Chapter.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Albeit that yet our knowledge and appearance what we be, is vnperfecte, and that we as yet beholde the maieſtie of God, (as it were through a glaſſe, &amp; in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) or in a cloude. Yet ſhall we hereafter
<pb facs="tcp:13420:34"/> beholde him face to face.</hi> Thus doe we waite for neuertheleſſe theſe thinges in the meane ſeaſon in bleſſed hope. For we beholde our ſelues likewiſe, by our ſelues, childiſhlye, and looke for the deliueraunce of our bodies, for we ſhal be throughly bleſſed, albeit in hope. This hoping neuertheleſſe, that we ſée, is no hope, for how can a man hope for that he ſeeth? But if we hope for that we ſée not, then doe we looke after it by patience,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. 13.</note> the 13. to the Romans Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth belong hereunto, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is there to the time of ſufferinges, theſe two ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, patience, and hope, for with theſe two winges ſpecially, faith and hope, you muſt enforce your ſelfe to flée vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen. But patience muſte fight the battell with the dragon, which wil ſtrengthen and hinder your way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
               <p>Ninthely, nowe welbeloued, ſéeing that your ſickneſſe ſomwhat lingereth, and that God for a time doeth prolong his helpe and deliuerance, and will not ſoudenly, as we deſire, pray, and think,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13420:34"/> deliuer you, but wil awhile try &amp; proue your faith, for your faith muſt be tried by aduerſitie, and temptation, as gold is tried and proued in the fire: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt be patient. For albeit our Lorde GOD for a time, withdraweth his merciful helpe, yet will he not long be abſent. It ſhould not ſtande with his godly nature &amp; mercie, that he ſhoulde for euer forſake you, being his childe through faith in Chriſte. Wherfore, though you a little while for the time of your ſuffering muſt ſing with Chriſte, the lamentable ſong, and ſay, <hi>My GOD my GOD, wherefore haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> yet will not God long tarrie nor be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he ſuffereth you to ſwimme a while, but not vtterly ſo be drowned, he ſuffereth you peraduenture one day, but he will by and by afterwards raiſe you vp againe, and giue you euerlaſting peace and happineſſe. Therefore, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit you doe not for a little time ſée Chriſte in his throne of grace, yet ſhall you ſhortly ſée him againe, Iohn the .16.<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.</note> For his anger, that is to ſay, his fatherly
<pb facs="tcp:13420:35"/> correction endureth but the twinkling of an eye, and he hath pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to ſaue. And therefore doeth our Lorde God him ſelfe comfort you in the Prophet Eſai the .54.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſaie. 54.</note> Cap, ſaying thus. <hi>Beholde I haue hidden my face a little from thee, in the ſhort time of anger: neuertheles, I will haue mercie vpon thee with my conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall fauour,</hi> ſaith the Lorde God our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerer. Therefore ſaith Saint Paule the ſeconde Epiſtle the .4. Chap. to the Cor.<note place="margin">Cor. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Although our trouble, whiche is but tranſitorie and eaſie (though we thinke it ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry heauie, much and long) yet doth it breede and bring foorth an euerlaſting and a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilous weightie and vnmeaſurable dignitie and estimation vnto vs, whiche we cannot beholde with theſe eyes, but with inuiſible eyes. For no eye hath ſene, nor no eare heard, nor no mans heart can expreſſe that GOD hath prepared for them that loue him.</hi> Eſai. 64.<note place="margin">Eſaie. 64.</note> And .1. Cor. 2.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 2.</note> But in theſe things muſt Gods children a while be pacient, ſuffering, poliſhed and preſſed, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bethinke and conſider theſe comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſayings, which be ſpoken vnto vs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13420:35"/> as to children the .12. to the Hebr.<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.</note> out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Prouerbes of Solomon in the third Chapter, as it is there written.<note place="margin">Prouerb. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot ſlightly, but earneſtly regard the Lordes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>haſtening or correction, and diſpaire not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen he puniſheth thee. For whom the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oueth him doeth hee puniſh, &amp; correcteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uery childe that he taketh to him ſelfe.</hi> If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou abide his correction patiently, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oeth God ſhewe him ſelfe as to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hildren, for where is a ſonne whome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he father doeth not correct. Howbeit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uery chaſtening while it is a doing, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oeth not reioyce vs, but maketh vs ſad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd penſiue, but afterward it bringeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ioyful fruite of righteouſnes, to them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat be exerciſed in it. And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith Saint Iames in his firſt Chapter.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſteme it for a perfect ioy when you chance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o fall into many temptations, and know, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our faith if it be perfect worketh pacience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut patience ſhall perfectly abide vnto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nde. To the end it may be perfect and haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t all no manner of imperfection..</hi> For, <hi>He that abideth to the ende he ſhalbe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d,</hi> Matth. the .10.<note place="margin">Matth. 10.</note> Therfore a Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:13420:36"/> may well boaſt him ſelfe of trouble, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we knowe, that <hi>Trouble bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth patience, patience bringeth experience, experience bringeth hope, hope will neuer be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. Let vs not be aſhamed, for the loue of GOD is powred out into our heartes through the holy ghoſt, which is giuen vnto vs,</hi> the .6.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> to the Rom.</p>
               <p>Thus ſhall you in patience looke for the mercifull helpe and viſitation of God, and in your heart ſing the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt ſong of thankeſgiuing, of the holy man Simeon,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> Luke the ſecond, and ſay thus: <hi>Lord nowe letteſt thou thy ſeruaunt departe in peace, as thou haſt ſaide. For mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluation, whiche thou haſt prepared for al people. To be a light to lighten the heathen, and to be the praiſe of all thy people of Iſrael.</hi> For I haue nowe (God be praiſed) obteined y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of thy ſaluation, which is in the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſinnes: Through the tender mercie of our God whereby he hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited vs, that came from aboue, <hi>That he might appeare to them that ſatte in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in the ſhadowe of death, and leade
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13420:36"/> our feete into the way of peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 2.</note> as Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias did ſing, Luke the ſecond.</p>
               <p>The tenth, welbeloued, your ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe continueth and doth not leaue off, and you thinke long for helpe, yet muſt you giue ouer theſe things, ye muſt not ſhrinke from God, nor be faint harted, but in patience haue a perfect and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt hope, that God will not be long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, though he ſéeme to tarrie, but or it be long will come and help you: yea, the longer God withdraweth from you his gratious helpe, the mightier and better hereafter will your helpe and comfort be: for God ſtandeth yet a while behind the wal, as a louing and friendly bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, and looketh through the window priuily in vpon his ſpouſe, and marketh whether ſhe doth ſo loue her bridgrome, that ſhe will wayt and tarrie for him, and that ſhe may perceiue that he at the length will reache out his hande to her, plucke her foorth, &amp; bring her home. His loue is as ſtrong as death, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it is hidden very life and felicitie. Therfore deſpaire not euen in the very
<pb facs="tcp:13420:37"/> daunger of death, and ſing once againe with this congregation, and with all the holy elected Saintes of GOD in your heart, in this manner.</p>
               <p>In the middeſt of our life we be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about with death, whom ſhal we ſéeke to for help, that we may get grace? thou only, oh Lord, art high, we be ſorry for our miſdéedes which haue offended thée, oh holy Lord God, oh mightie Lord God, oh holy merciful Sauiour euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting God, let vs not be drowned in the bitter danger of death. Lord haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs.</p>
               <p>In the middeſt of death, the gaping of hell aſſaulteth vs, who can deliuer vs from this great peril? that canſt thou Lorde alone doe, thy great mercy hath compaſſion on our complaint and great miſerie, Holy Lorde GOD, oh mightie Lord God, oh holy mercifull Sauiour, oh euerlaſting God, let vs not diſpaire for the déepe pit of hell. Lord haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs.</p>
               <p>In the middeſt of the ſorrowes of hell our ſinnes lye hard vpon vs, then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13420:37"/> ſhal we flée from hence? where may we abide in ſafetie? to the Lord Chriſte alone. Thou haſt ſhead thy bloud that hath ſatiſfied for our ſinns, oh holy Lord God, oh holy mightie God, oh holy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull ſauiour, oh thou euerlaſting God, let vs not fall backe from the comfort of our faith, Lord haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
               <p>Behold, thus ſhall we reioyce in our greateſt daunger, and withall our heart <hi>Sing vnto our Lord God a ſong of thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, which is the right ſacrifice of than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</hi> Pſal. 50.<note place="margin">Pſalme. 50.</note> Theſe be the right ſingers to God, when the whole armie of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſinge with vs, and giue vnto God prayſe and thankes. Therefore nowe without all feare and trembling, hope vppon the endleſſe mercy of God, that this your trouble and heauineſſe, and dangerous gronings and ſighings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vp to Gods compaſſion, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neare inough to his heart. But herein ſhall you ſtay your ſelf and hope, and ſo ſhall you be ſtrengthened, Eſaie 30.<note place="margin">Eſaie 30.</note> And thus ſhal you conclude in your heart, and earneſtly hope, and with S.
<pb facs="tcp:13420:38"/> Paule ſay thus, Rom. 8.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>I knowe certein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that neither death nor life, neither An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel nor principalitie, neither power preſent or to come, neither aboue nor beneath, nor none other creature may remoue vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi> To be ſhort, <hi>Who will accuſe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected of God, God is hee that doth iustifie, who can condemne vs? Christe is hee that died, yea rather that is riſen againe, which ſitteth on Gods right hand, and forgiueth vs.</hi> Nowe if death, ſinne, diuel, hel, all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, aduerſitie, and plague fall vpon me in heapes, yet will I before you all abide ſtill in my God, and ſtill remaine a childe of euerlaſting ioy and felicitie. Amen.</p>
               <p>The eleuenth, though welbeloued, that ye do perſuade your ſelfe as though God himſelfe were againſt you, and were angrie with you by reaſon of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed ſinnes, yet ye ſhall not be afraid nor diſmaye your ſelfe. For God many times doth proue his, &amp; appeareth vnto them outwardly as though he were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie angrie with them, as thoughe he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13420:38"/> would lay hands on them, puniſh them, and vtterly condemne them. Therefore ſéeing God firſt will make you to liue, he wil before hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble you, &amp; ſeeing he will bring you to heauen, he will firſt caſte you downe into hel. For,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Lord ſley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and reuiueth, God doth caſt vs into hel, and leadeth vs out againe.</hi> As holy Anna ſaith, the firſt of Samuel the 2. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this temptation, learne rightly and properly to knowe the nature and propertie of God. He meaneth not euil towardes you, but by this meanes he tryeth your faith and your hope, that ye may be found to be perfect. Surely, it is a hard fight to wage battel with God him ſelfe, as the good Patriarch Iaacob did a whole night long, but at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> length he had the victorie and lay aboue: And therefore was he called Iſrael. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alſo muſt the ſpirituall Iſrael doe, and in ſpiritual fight preuaile and haue the ouerhand. And to be ſhort, at length it muſt come to paſſe with you thus, that you muſt nowe onely beléeue vpon hope where no hope is, Rom. 8.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> For,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:39"/> 
                  <hi>True faith is a certeine aſſuraunce to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine thoſe things, and not doubt on, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we can neither beholde nor ſee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ebr. 11.</note> Heb. 11.</p>
               <p>This is your caſe, for in outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and féeling, ye ſée nothing but death him ſelfe, but the eyes of your faith looke further, for they ſée life in the middeſt of death, in the middeſt of ſinne true ioy and perfection: in the middeſt of hell, heauen: in the middeſt of Gods anger and puniſhment, grace and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting welfare. This is ſurely a ſtrang and wonderfull ſight, and this is alſo an excellent, paſſing, and fine knowledge, a cunning aboue all cunnings, whiche declareth vnto vs, howe we ſhall find in death, perfect life, howe we in the dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt miſerie ſhall be comforted, how we in the greateſt doubtes ſhall be inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to be ſhort, when it appeareth vnto vs, that we are vtterly vndone, euery body hath forſaken vs, euery body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth their ſuccour from vs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes there appeareth nothing but deſtruction, and vtter vndoing, we ſhall make much adoe, and wonderfully
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13420:39"/> buſie our ſelues, and in our reaſon and opinion, knowe not whether to goe, we ſeeme to liue, and yet we dye, we ſée and féele, and yet be in the middeſt of death. But here we muſt lay aſide all féeling, ſeeing, vnderſtanding, wiſedome, and reaſon, and vtterly forſake them, and with theſe comforts, to be merrie in the middeſt of death, and ſlide through it as through ſléep, to the bleſſed hope, that God will through his mercy in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Chriſte euerlaſtingly kéepe vs, and make vs inioy his bleſſings. What ſo euer Gods wil be, let things appeare outwardly as they will, let thinges goe and ſtand with vs as God will, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue we ſtedfaſtly, that Gods grace and goodneſſe will defende vs for euer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to all mans reaſon and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for he will not aſcribe our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor giue the honour, glory, &amp; prayſe thereof, vnto vs or our workes, eyther to our indeuour, but vnto his endleſſe mercy, that at the laſt day we ſhould &amp; muſt confeſſe, that our ſaluation was not in our power, in our doings, in our
<pb facs="tcp:13420:40"/> will and might, but onely in the mercy and onely grace of God, which we haue obteined through Chriſt our onely Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. For which grace and good will, we are bound to giue to God continual thankes, and only laude and prayſe his holy name, and aſcribe vnto him all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, power, might, and maieſtie: behold thus ſhal you fight and ſtriue with God, againſt god, and puſh and enforce your ſelfe as it were through very thiſtles &amp; thornes, to enter into heauen, and there againe beginne in your heart to ſing the comfortable ſong of the holy Dauid, Pſalme. 73.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal. 73.</note> where he thus ſingeth, <hi>If I haue onely thee my Lord and my God, I paſſe of nothing, neither in heauen, nor in earth, though my body and my ſoul be in contempt, yet art thou my God alway my heartes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and my health.</hi> And then will GOD comfort you, and ſay thus, Eſaie. 41.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aie. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>Be not afraid, I am with thee, be not faint hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen thee, I will helpe thee out, I will holde thee vppe, through the ſtrength of my righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Twelfthly, if welbeloued, many aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13420:40"/> and temptations fall vpon you, as it were by heapes, yet let them not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſmay or diſcourage you, for ſathan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth willingly beſtowe all his cunning, when the matter commeth to the puſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r extremitie. If he could not ouercome you in your life time, whileſt ye were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n perfect health, then wil he now more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trongly withſtande and aſſault you, now in your weakneſſe. Therfore now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earne, and be expert in deede, what the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubtiltie and craft of the wicked fiende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, what ſleightes and deuiſes he vſeth and practiſeth againſt you: for his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and condition is with great rage and fierceneſſe to ſet vpon men, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to you very ſtoutly, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually with many and diuers temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and thinketh thus with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſundrie aſſaults and forces to diſmay, amaze, enféeble, match, &amp; make deſperate a féeble, and vnexperienced Chriſtian, wherby he may driue an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>experienced Chriſtian at the laſt, to put him ſelfe at all aduentures, to giue ouer, and yeld him ſelfe to euery temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:41"/> and to be ouercome, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that at the laſt, he may fall into doubt, yeald him ſelfe wholy priſoner to the wicked enimie, and to ſubmit him ſelfe vnto him, from which our Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you of his good grace, with his holy ſpirite. Amen.</p>
               <p>Therfore if now at the laſt any ſuch come vnto you, and that ſathan will lay vnto you that God (after his maieſtie) is a great deale too high &amp; mightie to haue any regarde, or to make any reckoning of you, be gratious to you, &amp; ſhewe you mercy, then let ſuch high imaginations and thoughts paſſe, which touch the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable maieſtie of God, and come from thence to Chriſtes humanitie, and howe he tooke vppon him our nature, and beginne at his cradell to take holde vpon God that is moſt high, and too farr aboue our reach, For, <hi>In Christ dwelleth the whole fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily.</hi> Coloſ. 2.<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> And as Chriſte him ſelfe ſaith, Io. 14.<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>He that ſeeth me</hi> (ſaith Chriſte to Philip) <hi>hee ſeeth the father. Doeſt thou not beleue that I am in the father, and that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13420:41"/> the father is in me.</hi> Therefore thus begin with Saint Thomas, Iohn 20.<note place="margin">Iohn. 20.</note> and call thus vpon Chriſt, &amp; ſay, <hi>My God, &amp; my Lorde.</hi> Thus ſhall you ſéeke out the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God, finde him, and take holde on him, that is only in Chriſte: there is the euerlaſting godhead and high maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie onely to be ſought and found, and without our Lorde Chriſt ſhall you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer finde God, nor lay hand vpon him: therefore thus cry with the woman of Chanaan, <hi>Oh thou ſonne of Dauid, haue mercy vpon me.</hi> Matth. 15.<note place="margin">Matth. 15</note>
               </p>
               <p>The thirtéenth, And if beloued, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation after this ſort would preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, as though god were not nigh you, neither in heauen, nor in earth, to ſuccour and helpe you, but that he doth vtterly deſpiſe and forſake you, &amp; that ſathan woulde lay and caſt before you mocking and blaſphemie, and ſay, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, where is thy God, vppon whome thou haſt ſo long truſted? beholde howe well he heareth thée? beholde what haſte he maketh to help thée? how wiſely haſt thou committed thy ſelfe to him? either
<pb facs="tcp:13420:42"/> what great care hath he of thée? he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth thee to ſticke faſt, and ſtarue in thy greateſt danger &amp; perils. Oh, ſurely this is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou takeſt for the right God, and whom thou honoureſt, &amp; calleſt vpon, elſe would he neuer ſuffer thée now ſo miſerably to be deſtroyed &amp; periſh, &amp;c. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſuch or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie of ſathan is laid before you, then holde your peace, &amp; be quiet at ſuch blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, &amp; neuer diſpute with ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by &amp; by turne you to Chriſte crucified, to Gods ſonne him ſelfe, and cal vpon him with your whole hart, that he will come and ayde you with his holy ſpirite, and ſtrike ſathan, that he may be driuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from you, and call vppon Chriſte your mediatour onely, that he wil ſtand betwéene the high maieſtie of God and you miſerable ſinner, and do like a good mediatour, &amp; will withdrawe his great and mightie righteouſneſſe and iuſtice, take your ſinnes vpon him, and ſo goe before you, intreate, and reconcile you. Otherwiſe will the maieſtie of God be too much, too highe, and terrible, ſo that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13420:42"/> you ſhall before God be afraid, amazed, and out of countenance. Therefore take this Lord and mediatour by the hand, if ye will drawe nigh to God, and haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to do with him. For this medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour hath ben a long time ordeined by God himſelfe for vs, that we through him might be reconciled to God, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth Saint Paul. 1. Tim. 2.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>There is one God, and one mee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diatour betweene God and man: namely, the man Ieſus Christe, that hath giuen him ſelfe for all for deliueraunce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourtéenth, If welbeloued, your ſinne doth nowe accuſe you, for that you not onely in your youthe, when your body was ſound and luſtie, did ſinne &amp; offend God: but alſo euen now in your ſickneſſe, ye haue diſpleaſed God by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, murmuring, miſbeléefe, &amp;c. as we al be borne in ſinne, be ſinners, and ſo remaine and abide, till we come to our graue: therefore let not your ſinne in any caſe make you deſpaire, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege and confeſſe, and accuſe your ſelfe before your Lord God, and be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:13420:43"/> for them with all your heart, aſke mercy therefore before God, in Chriſte our Lorde. For it is impoſſible in this life, that in the ſight of God we ſhoulde be found ſo cleare, pure, and without fault or ſinne, as holy Saint Iohn wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth .1. Iohn .1. where he ſaith thus, <hi>If we ſay we haue no ſinne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 2</note> 
                  <hi>then ſhall we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues, and the trueth is not in vs.</hi> Therefore in the middeſt of ſinne we haue this onely comfort, (when we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſinne, the vnquietneſſe of our conſcience, and the trouble of our hearts cumbereth vs) that we call then vpon our atturney Chriſt the Lord, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intent that he for euer be gratious vnto vs, &amp; intreat &amp; ſpeak for vs towards his deare father, as then Saint Iohn (when we ſticke in ſinne) comforteth vs. 1. Ioh. 2.<note place="margin">Iohn 2</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>If any man ſinne, yet haue we an aduocate to the father Ieſus Christe, that maketh vs righteous, and he is the attonement for our ſinnes.</hi> From hence ſhall you ſéeke youre refuge and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, and in euery aſſaulte of your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, comfort your ſelfe, that you haue
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13420:43"/> ſuch a peacemaker before God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whome the father doth accept and allowe, that can ſpeake well, and is elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent, and can handle your cauſe, and plead for you beſt. Surely, this is a gret and a perfect comfort, that we haue our fleſhe and bloud ſitting aboue at Gods right hand the father, which doeth take vppon him the whole progenie of man, intreateth for vs, pleadeth our cauſe, &amp; turneth the wrath of GOD from vs, as holy S. Paule alſo witneſſeth. Rom. 8.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>Chriſt is at the right hand of God, and maketh interceſſion for vs.</hi> This is his holy office, that he deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth wretched ſinners from Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, defendeth and kéepeth them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore flée only to this Lord Chriſte, when your ſinne grieueth or troubleth you.</p>
               <p>The fiftéenth, If now in theſe long lingering aſſaults and conflicts, welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, your heart waxe cold, be vnlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, &amp; drowſie, as you thinke that there is no more faith in your heart, and that for vnluſt you can neither pray nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, yet ſhall you not therefore giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:13420:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13420:45"/> or be afraid: for the Lord God brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his many times ſo déepe vnder the croſſe, that they can neither beléeue nor hope, and thinke with them ſelues, that their heartes be vtterly cold and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: yea, very ſtiffe, that neither faith, loue, prayer, nor no good thought can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more appeare in their heartes. If this great &amp; ſore temptation ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen alſo to trouble you, yet deſpaire not therefore, but be of good cheare, &amp; thinke thus with your ſelfe: I perceiue that I muſt altogether be naked and vnclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, and put off all that I haue, &amp; ſpoile my ſelfe of euery thing that I haue or may doe, all that euer I haue falleth cleane from me, and forſaketh me. My louing bridegrome our lord Chriſt wil cloath me anew, adorne and dreſſe me, and trimme me with all his iewels. Therefore call now againe vpon him, as vppon your highe prieſt, that he will haue mercie vpon you, intreat and pray for you, and wil haue heartie compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your weakeneſſe. For, <hi>We haue not an high prieſt that can not take co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pasſion of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eb. 5.</note>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:13420:45"/> 
                  <hi>our feebleneſſe, but ſuch an high prieſt that hath beene thoroughly tempted, and is like vnto vs in all things (except in ſinne.) Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs goe vnto him, with ioy to his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſeate, that wee may obteine mercie and finde grace, at that time when helpe ſhalbe neceſſarie for vs. Heb. 5.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here haue you a very great comfort, that Chriſt is your high prieſt. Call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him earneſtly, that he wil ſend into your colde heart his holy ſpirite, which ſhall call within you, father, father, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing father: Euen then ſhall the holy Ghoſt helpe vp your weakenes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth for you alſo mightily, with ſighings not able to be expreſſed. Rom. viij.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Then alſo doeth Chriſt himſelfe pray for you, like the high prieſt before the father, &amp; ſuffereth not your weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be laid to your charge, deſpiſeth you not, becauſe of your vntowardnes, your ignorance, or faint heart: for this high prieſt hath great compaſſion with our weakenes, he doth not only intreat for vs, but alſo he ſheweth foorth before the father his innocent bodie, which he
<pb facs="tcp:13420:46"/> hath offered vppon the Croſſe for you, a perfect ſacrifice for euer. Heb. 9.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ebr. 9.</note> As alſo S. Paule witneſſeth, Epheſ. 5.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pheſ. 5.</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>Chriſt hath loued vs, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen himſelfe for vs for a gift and offering vnto God for a ſweete ſauour.</hi> This is the noble gift, and this is the auaileable of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for you, which is richly accepted before God.</p>
               <p>Thus haue you now your high prieſt Chriſte oure Lord himſelfe, the altar wherevppon he was offered his croſſe, the offering his cleane vnſpotted and pure bodie. Nowe marke how and in what manner or faſhion Chriſte your high prieſt did hang vpon the croſſe, for ſuch maner of hanging is very comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, if one would behold it with belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing eyes.</p>
               <p>For firſt, Chriſt hangeth vppon the Croſſe with his armes and hands ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out, to ſignifie, that he is readie to giue grace, accept and imbrace with his armes all poore and wretched ſinners: for he hangeth there for the comforte of poore ſinners, &amp; reacheth out his armes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13420:46"/> to troubled conſciences.</p>
               <p>Secondarily, his féete alſo be heaued vp and faſt nailed, in token that he tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth there for all wretched ſinners: for he wil not ſtart aſide nor flie from you, but will continually be found, and tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth for you.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he turneth his face and not his backe to you, he boweth downe his face like vnto a gentle and milde Lord to the prayers of all poore and troubled perſons, will gladly with all his heart heare them, he is willing and readie, he openeth his eares wide, wherby he will certeinly heare you.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, his heart is wide open to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you, for it is pearced with a ſpeare, whereby he may haue heartie compaſſion with your aduerſitie, and will ſet your trouble very neare vnto his owne heart.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, he weareth a crowne of thorne vpon his head, to ſignifie, that he will be your king, and defend and kéepe you from all miſfortune, from ſinne, from death, from the diuell, and from hell.
<pb facs="tcp:13420:47"/> This is a maruellous gratious and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beholding to all troubled ſinners, for he hangeth in the middle of ſinners, as a ſinner, bycauſe he will receiue all miſerable, forſaken ſinners, giue them grace, and preſerue and kéepe them for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Hereafter followe certeine prayers, whiche may be ſaid before the ſicke body, if the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe haue any continuance, whereby ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the ſicke bodies heart may be touched, moued, and kindled, that the ſickneſſe may not preuaile, and haue the ouerhand vpon the ſicke.</head>
               <p>Firſt welbeloued, let vs lift vp our heartes to almightie God, and put him in remembraunce of his gratious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which he hath made vs at our holy baptiſme: therfore ſay after me, though not with your mouth, yet with your heart chiefly thus.</p>
               <p>MY Lorde and God, remember the holy couenant whiche thou haſt made with me in my holy baptiſme, wherin thou haſt receiued me to grace,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13420:47"/> and to be thy childe, and promiſed me, that I beléeuing and béeing baptiſed, ſhould be ſaued. Marke. 16.<note place="margin">Mark. 16.</note> Séeing then thou Lorde haſt ſo aſſuredly bound thy ſelfe vnto me, to be my gratious, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, true, and louing father, my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and hope is alonely in thée, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſtedfaſtly beléeue, that as ſurely as I am baptiſed in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, that thou wilt be my defender, deliuerer, and comforter, and helpe me out of all daunger, leade me and defend me from all perill, that neither ſinne, death, nor hell can hurt me. Therefore I will not deſpaire in all aduerſitie, and euen in the extremitie of death turn my heart vnto thée, and ſtedfaſtly beléeue, that thou wilt neuer forſake me, but giue vnto me euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe, through the deſeruing of Chriſte my Lord and Sauiour.</p>
               <p>Secondarily, welbeloued, let vs now againe turne our ſelues vnto almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, from whome commeth al help, and call vpon him from the bottome of
<pb facs="tcp:13420:48"/> our hearts inwardly, as our onely God and father, and ſay thus.</p>
               <p>OH almightie euerlaſting God, and father, I being full of all vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and ſinne, come vnto thée, and yet am I thy welbeloued childe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſéeing thou art the euerlaſting true God, I comfort my ſelfe with thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that thou wilt faithfully performe all that thou haſt promiſed me. Nowe thou haſt ſaide, Matth. 11.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atth. 11.</note> When I am troubled in my conſcience with ſinne, care, néede, heauineſſe, and am heauie laden many wayes, and I repaire vnto thée, that then thou wilt help me, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue me in my heauineſſe.</p>
               <p>For as much as thou art my welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued father, and I am thy childe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe I looke for from thée wholy, all good things, help &amp; comfort in al trouble, for thou art not an earthly father, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſomtime can neither help him ſelfe, nor his children, but thou Lorde art the almightie &amp; heauenly father, that wilt willingly with all thy heart helpe me, &amp;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13420:48"/> likewiſe art able ſo to doe, by reaſon of thy almightie power. For thou art the maker of heauen and of earth, thou haſt all thinges in thy hande and power, all cretures of heauen and of earth be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto thée, and muſt ſerue and obey thée euen as thou liſteſt. Therfore Lord deſpiſe me not, though I be a very wret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched ſinner altogether, for theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſéeing that thou by thy worde haſt commaunded and promiſed, that I ſhal be heard in what daunger and trouble ſo euer I be, when I call vpon thée, and that then I ſhall honour thée, and euer acknowledge thée to be the true and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry God: ſéeing I perceiue, that what ſo euer thou promiſeſt, that thou doſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme effectually. Therefore beléeue I certeinly thy worde, that thou wilt not denie it, but vndoubtedly perfourme whatſoeuer thou haſt once ſpoken: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſéech thée, from the bottome of my heart, that thou wilt help me out of my trouble and ſickneſſe, and neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me, but gratiouſly ſend me thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly helpe, and deliuer me from my
<pb facs="tcp:13420:49"/> diſtreſſe. For there is no body vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I can perceiue any helpe or goodneſſe, but only vpon thée, therefore helpe thou me my lord and God, but not according to my deſerts, worthineſſe, or goodnes, but through the deſerts of thy ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, which hath purchaſed vnto me, from thée, all grace and fatherly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, him doſt thou loue, and haſt great pleaſure in him, and therfore thou wilt not forſake me for his ſake, but rather ſheweſt vnto me all goodneſſe: therfore I commit my ſelf wholy vnto thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and fatherly goodneſſe, and put my whole cauſe vnto thée, as to my louing father, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wilt deliuer me out of all this trouble, griefe, weaknes, &amp; paines, when it ſhal pleaſe thy godly will: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not appoint vnto thée ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time nor ſpace, but earneſtly hope vpon thée, that thou wilt heare me, and defend me, though my caſe appeare ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtraunge, and as impoſſible as it may be: for thou art almightie, haſt might and power ouer all things, and beſides this, thou art my father, and art willing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13420:49"/> to doe it, if it were nowe neceſſarie. Therfore at thy hand I looke for al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, be it vnto me according vnto thy true promiſe. Amen.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, moreouer welbeloued, let vs once againe lift vp our heartes and mindes vnto him, from whome all help and goodneſſe commeth, chiefly vnto the father of all light, which giueth euery good gift, &amp; gratiouſly heareth vs. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſéeing that your paines, neceſſitie, miſerie, and griefes ſtil continue, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray vnto our Lord God, with holy Dauid, and ſay thus, <hi>Oh Lord, puniſh me not in thine anger, &amp; correct me not in thine me. Lord be gratious vnto me, for I am fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: heale me Lorde, for my bones be afraide. Turne thee Lord, and deliuer my ſoule, help me according to thy pleaſure: be not far from me, for trouble is at hand, for here is none that can helpe. Remember Lorde thy mercy and thy goodneſſe, which hath ben ſince the world beganne. Remember not the ſinnes of my youth, nor mine offences, but thinke vpon me after thy mercy, and according to thy goodneſſe. Lorde haue mercy vppon my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:50"/> which be very great, turne thee to me, &amp; be gratious vnto me, for I am forſaken and in miſerie, the heauineſſe of my heart is great, lead me out of my neceſſitie and need. Behold my miſerie and distreſſe, and forgiue me all mine offences. Lorde be gratious vnto me according to thy goodneſſe, and blot out all my ſinnes, after thy great mercy, waſh me cleane from mine offences, &amp; make me pure from my ſinnes, for I acknowledge myne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and my miſdeedes be euer before me. On thee alone haue I ſinned, and haue done euill in thy ſight. Hide thy face from my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and blot out all mine offences. Make a cleane heart within me, and giue me a newe right ſpirit. Caſt me not out of thy ſight, and take not thine holy Ghost from me. Comfort me againe with thy helpe, and giue in me the ſpirite of peace. Be vnto me a ſtrong tower, whether I may for euer flee for ſuccour: for thou hast promiſed to helpe me, for thou art my rocke, and my hill. Oh Lorde, I cry vnto thee, bicauſe thou art gratious, Lord for thy great goodneſſe heare me with thy true help, heare me Lorde, for thy goodneſſe is comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, turne thee vnto me according to thy
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13420:50"/> great mercy. Lord be not farre from me. My God make hast to helpe me. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thee Lord do I trust, God helpe me out of all my needs, and ſet me at libertie. Looke vppon me, and heare me Lord my God. Lighten myne eyes, that I may ſleepe ſoundly in the middest of death. I loue thee with all my heart, Lorde God my ſtrength, Lorde my rocke, my hill, my deliuerer, my God, my castell, vpon whome I trust, my buckler and horne of my ſaluation, my defence. Lord in thee doe I trust, let me neuer be confounded. Deliuer me for thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſake. Bowe downe thine eares to me, make ſpeede to help me. Be vnto me a ſtrong rocke and an hill, where thou maiest helpe me. For thou art my rocke and my hill, and for thy name ſake leade me and bring mee foorth, come to my ſoule and deliuer it, keepe my ſoule, and deliuer me. Let me not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, for I trust in thee. Lorde quicken me for thy name ſake, leade my ſoule out of this daunger, for thy righteouſneſſe ſake, for my ſoule fainteth in my bodie, and the feare of death is falen vpon me. Feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling compaſſeth me, and loathſomeneſſe is falen vpon me. I lie with my ſoule among the
<pb facs="tcp:13420:51"/> Lions, therefore, oh Lorde, heare my prayers, and let my crie come vnto thee. Hide not thy face from me in my neede. Bowe downe thine eare vnto me, when I call vpon thee, then heare me betime. Nowe Lord wherein ſhall I comfort me? I hope vpon thee, leaue off from troubling me, that I may refreſhe my ſelfe before I goe hence, and come no more againe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>If it pleaſe any man to ſay all the whole Pſalms, to be ſaid to the ſicke, I will not complaine vppon him. Therfore they that liſt may when he liſt ſometime take theſe Pſalmes hereafter following, and read the ſame to the ſicke, and ſometime make ſome ſhorte rehearſall of them, and with them comfort the ſicke body, ſpecially the 25. 51. 70. 71. 77. 87. 88. 103. 130. &amp;c. And if neede require, a man may often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate them or take ſome comfortable part of them, and alſo like comfortable ſayinges out of my litle booke, called The ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, all which for ſhortneſſe I leaue heere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched.</head>
               <p>Fourthly, if the ſick bodie draw on, and is neare his ende, then ſay our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe, that is, the xij. Articles of our holy faith thus.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:13420:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>J Beleeue in God the father Almightie, maker of heauen and earth: And in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ his onely ſonne, our Lord, whiche was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the virgin Marie, ſuffered vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified dead and buried, hee deſcended into hell, he roſe againe the third day from the dead, he aſcended into heauen, he ſitteth on the right hand of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Almightie, from thence he ſhal come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beleeue in the holy ghoſt, The holy catholique Church, The communion of Saintes, The forgiuenes of ſinnes, The reſurrection of the bodie, and the life euerlaſting. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh higheſt comfort in all trouble, helpe, that we neither feare ſhame nor death, that our ſenſes be not diſmayed, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enimie accuſeth vs, Lord haue pittie vppon vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fiftly, if the partie lye long in a traunce: For I haue many times ſeene, that ſome haue lyen a long time (as it were) in a traunce, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward haue begunne againe to ſpeake, and haue ſaid, that they very well heard and did vnderſtand what hath then beene ſaid vnto them. Therefore they that will, may rehearſe
<pb facs="tcp:13420:52"/> to the ſicke, this ſhort expoſition of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe.</head>
               <p>I put all my truſt, hope, and comfort, onely in the méere grace and mercie of God, that he onely himſelfe can helpe me, and none other creature (howe holy ſoeuer he be) in all my néede and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And ſéeing he is my father, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue ſtedfaſtly, that he with all his hart will gladly helpe me, neuer forſake me neither in this world, nor in the world to come. And becauſe he is almightie God, I beléeue that he can defend me, and kéepe me, from all that is againſt me: For he onely is ſtrong ynough for mine enimie, by reaſon of his almightie power. And ſéeing he is the creatour of heauen and earth, I beléeue he can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund all other creatures, that none of them ſhall haue any power ouer me to my harme, without his fatherly good will.</p>
               <p>Therefore do I looke for onely from this almightie God, father, &amp; creatour, all good things and euerlaſting life. For all thinges come onely from him, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13420:52"/> are giuen vnto him: for he will giue himſelfe wholy and fully vnto me, with all that he is, and hath with heauen and earth, with al creatures, that they muſt ſerue me, and profite me, and further me toward euerlaſting life.</p>
               <p>I beléeue with all my heart, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the onely begotten ſonne of the father, from the beginning, hath for my ſake taken vpon him mans nature, and that he was conceiued of the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the holy virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as a right naturall mother, and that that man is very truly God as an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and vndiuided perſon of God and man. And that this ſonne of God &amp; Marie, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, hath for me wretched ſinner ſuffered, was for me crucified, and dead. Wherby he hath deliuered me from ſinne, from death, and from the euerlaſting wrath of God, by his innocent bloud: whiche in his owne perſon ſuffered the pangues of death, and hath taſted euerlaſting hell, and ouercome it, to the intent that I ſhould be reconciled with God, and be
<pb facs="tcp:13420:53"/> made Lord ouer al mine enimies. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, that except the death of this ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, I could neuer haue atteined vnto Gods fauour, and my ſaluation, neither by works, nor by any manner of deſert.</p>
               <p>I beléeue that Ieſus Chriſt my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is riſen from death for my righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and hath for my ſake taken death and hell priſoner, that they can neuer hurt me. For I confeſſe, that I ſhuld haue dyed for euer, if Ieſus Chriſt had not come to help me, and taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, as an innocent lamb, my ſinne, faults, curſe, and euerlaſting death, and hath ſatiſfied for me by his paſſion, and hath taken away the curſe for me. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, that he doth daily like a faithfull &amp; mercifull Mediatour, Sauiour, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prieſt, and Byſhop of my ſoule, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare and intreate for me.</p>
               <p>I beléeue, that Chriſte with God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually ruleth and fulfilleth all thinges, and that he is of equal power and might in heauen and in earth, Lorde ouer all Lordes, King ouer al Kings, and aboue
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13420:53"/> all cretures in heauen and in earth, and vnder the earth, aboue death and life, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ſinne and righteouſneſſe. This King and Lorde ſhall goe before me in my paſſion and death, ſhall hold battell, and fight for me, ſo that I with him ſhal be a Lorde ouer all mine enimies, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer.</p>
               <p>I beléeue that Chriſte crucified, ſhall come againe at the laſt day, and ſhall iudge and condemne thoſe that will not beléeue on him, but will defend me, and all faithfull from the terrible iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of damnation perpetuall, and ſay vnto vs, <hi>Come ye hyther, ye bleſsed of my Father, inherite the kingdome, whiche is prepared for you from the beeginning of the worlde, &amp; coet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beléeue in the holy Ghoſt, whiche with the father and the ſonne is one ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry God, and is procéeded from the father and the ſonne euerlaſtingly, and yet in one and the ſame godly being, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, an vndiuided perſon. I beléeue that I by him ſhall be adorned with faith, as with a liuing, euerlaſting, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:13420:54"/> gift and reward raiſed vp from death made frée from ſinne, and in my heart made merrie, comforted, and frée, and ſafe in conſcience. For this is my reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, that if I can finde in my hart ſuch witneſſe of Gods holy ſpirite, that then God will be my father, forgiue me my ſinne, and reward me with euerlaſting life.</p>
               <p>I beléeue, that the holy Ghoſte will help to beare mine infirmities, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate for me with vnſpeakable ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſtrengthen me, and light my hart, that I may knowe the excéeding riches, fatherly mercy that he hath giuen me, &amp; rewarded me with, of méere grace, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all my deſeruinges, onely through Chriſt his beloued ſonne, by whome the father hath rewarded me with thoſe his giftes. But the holy Ghoſt teacheth me to knowe all theſe thinges, he kindleth my heart, and lighteneth me, that theſe giftes come from aboue, as Chriſte hath promiſed vs, where he ſaith, Iohn. 7.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>He that beleueth in me (as the ſcripture ſaith) from his bodie ſhall flowe ſtreames of liuing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13420:54"/> waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beléeue, that there is vpon earth one Chriſtian church, that is the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or number, or aſſemblie, &amp; mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of all Chriſtians: in which there is one God, one Lord, one holy Ghoſt, one faith, one baptiſme, of which Churche Chriſt onely is the ſpouſe and huſband.</p>
               <p>I beléeue, that this Churche is the ſpirituall body, and that Chriſt onely is her head. I beléeue, that Chriſt is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of this his body and Church, and hath giuen him ſelfe for her, that he might make her holy, and hath cleanſed her through the waterbath of his word, that he may haue for him ſelfe a ſpeciall congregation, that neither hath ſpot nor wrinckle, or any other infirmitie, but that ſhe may be holy, and without fault, a piller and foundation of trueth.</p>
               <p>I beléeue, that in this Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and where ſo euer it be, that there alſo is forgiuing of ſinnes. There is the kingdome of grace, and right par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and that there is no ſaluation nor forgiuing of ſins, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out Chriſtendome.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13420:55"/>
               <p>I beléeue, that no man can be ſaued, except he be in this congregation and Church, as a liuely member planted in his owne body.</p>
               <p>I beléeue, that in this kingdome, there is not only once forgiuing of ſinnes, but as oft as we require and aſke it. For Chriſt is ſuch a maiſter of the hoſpitall, that doeth nothing elſe then looke to the ſicke, helpe them vp, ſtrengthen them, and maketh them whole, and as Eſaie ſaith, <hi>He will not breake a bruſed reede, nor he will not quench the ſmoaking flaxe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beléeue alſo the riſing of the body, that my body, whiche the wormes ſhall eate, ſhall ariſe againe, euen as it was before. For Chriſte at the laſt day ſhall raiſe it vppe, according to his promiſe, where he ſaith, Iohn. 6.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>This is the will of him that ſent me, that whoſoeuer ſeeth the ſonne, and beleeueth on him, ſhall haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life, and I will raiſe him at the last day.</hi> And, <hi>Whoſoeuer eateth of my fleſh, and drinketh of my bloud, hath euerlasting life, and I will raiſe him vp at the last day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beléeue, that after this life, there
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13420:55"/> ſhal be an euerlaſting life, ſo that I ſhal liue with Chriſt for euer, according to his promiſe, Iohn. 5.<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> where he ſaith, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily verily I ſay vnto you, who ſo euer hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth my worde, and beleeueth on him that ſent me, he hath euerlasting life, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not into iudgment, but he paſſeth clean through death to life.</hi> And, <hi>Whoſoeuer bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth on the ſonne, he hath euerlasting life.</hi> And, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily verily I ſay vnto you, if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will keepe my word, he ſhall not ſee euerlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death.</hi> Item, <hi>I am the breade of life,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt, Iohn. 6.<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note>) <hi>which is come from heauen, whoſoeuer ſhall eate of this breade, ſhall liue for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nowe welbeloued, ſéeing your time draweth on, ſtand ſtedfaſt vpon the only rocke, Chriſte our Lorde. Then can no ſtorme, no whirlwinde: yea, hell gates them ſelues can not remoue nor ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme you. For whoſoeuer beléeueth vpon our Lord God, ſhal neuer fall, nor be ouerturned, but ſhall abide for euer. Therfore call vpon our Lord God with your whole heart, for he is rich ouer all that call vpon him, and he will be nigh
<pb facs="tcp:13420:56"/> to all them that pray to him, to al them that call vpon him with their heartes, and graunteth all thinges which they that feare God do require, heareth their cry, and helpeth them. Therfore cal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God the moſt higheſt, in the name of Ieſus Chriſte, that he will ſhewe vnto you his great plentifull mercy, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wre out vpon you in the time of grace, richly his mercy. For ſéeing that our Lord is the ſpring it ſelfe of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Chriſt his onely begotten ſonne is the pipe &amp; conduit, wherby ſuch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of grace and mercy floweth, and is conueyed vnto vs, take yet againe faſt hold, in this your extreame néede, of the ouerflowing and floud of Gods grace, ſpecially Ieſus Chriſte, the ſcrine and caſket wherein Gods mercy is locked vp: for Chriſt is ful of grace and truth, Ioh. 1.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hn. 1.</note> For the euerlaſting ſonne of God hath brought with him ſuch great plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of grace, that he hath therewith ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the whole worlde: for heauen and earth is full thereof. And alſo Chriſte is full of truth, ſo that he is not alonly the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13420:56"/> truth it ſelfe, but alſo meaneth heartily and truly with vs, and will take to him ſelfe your ſoule, with great veritie and earneſtly. Therfore be of good comfort, that your name is written in the booke of life: you are fully cleanſed with the bloud of Chriſt, and annoynted with the holy Ghoſt: The ſame holy ſpirite aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth your heart, that you alſo be one of the very children of God. And albeit it doeth not as yet appeare what you be, yet knowe you, that when it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, then ye ſhall be like vnto him, Iohn. Chap. 8.<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note> For ye ſhall be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the godly nature. Pet. 2. Chap. 1.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> ſpecially when Chriſte our ſauiour ſhall come hither from heauen, and glorifie your miſerable body, and make it like vnto his glorified body, after his mighty power and working. Phil. 3.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> Chriſte Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the onely refuge of all poore peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſinners, he onely is your ſtrength, your comfort, hope, and ſtrong tower, in all néede and aduerſitie. Therefore goe without feare into the danger of death. Chriſt, in the twinckling of an eye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:13420:57"/> your euerlaſting king, will plucke you out againe, bring you to light, and make you righteous and liuing. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue your ſelf ouer valiantly from this life vnto death, and be not afraide, ſéeing that death hath loſt all his might and ſtrength on the faithfull. Chriſt the victorious conquerer hath taken from death al his ſtrength, ſo that from hence foorth he can no more hurt, wearie, or deuour any Chriſtian. Wherefore will ye then be diſmaide or afraide, for ſuche a ſhadow or viſar of death? Death may for a litle while roare &amp; whet his téeth, but he can do no more: for Chriſte hath taken his ſting from him, and likewiſe is Gods euerlaſting iudgment, through the Sauiour of the worlde, taken from you. And Chriſt the only ſonne of God, hath appeaſed the iuſtice of God, &amp; layde the ſame farr enough out of your way: So that from hencefoorth you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be called to appeare before the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of GOD, nor you ſhall not néede to appeare, neither aunſwere for your ſinne, bicauſe Ieſus your ſauiour
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13420:57"/> hath made you frée from it. Therefore chearefully appeale from the iudgment ſeate, vnto the throne of mercy, which is Chriſt your deliuerer, call earneſtly vpon the ſtoole of grace, whervpon gods mercy reſteth and dwelleth in Chriſte Ieſus, the ſonne of the higheſt, therfore can no complaint come againſt you, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinne, death, hell, nor ſathan him ſelfe. Chriſt is the true Lion of the tribe of Iuda, which for your ſakes hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued vtterly all your enimies, wiped &amp; blotted out all ſinne, and ſwallowed vp death: ſo there remaineth now no more, but that the body muſt ſuffer and abide only one litle ſhiuering and ſhrinking, after that you ſhal be perfectly ſafe and ſure. Fight therefore manfully as a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Rutter or Capteine, againſt the dragon and hell gates, then will Chriſt with the hoaſt &amp; armie of heauen, méete you, and receiue your ſoule, to carrie it with him into euerlaſting ioy and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ If any be diſpoſed, they may rehearſe againe to
<pb facs="tcp:13420:58"/> the ſicke, the twelue Articles of our beleefe, for they be the very ancor, yea, the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our beleefe, which wee can neuer ſufficiently meditate and thinke vpon. It is therefore very meete and neceſſarie, ſeeing in our youth wee bee baptiſed in them, that wee continually be fed with them: then ſhall wee ioyfully die in them. It were very good that we ſhould alwayes in time of our health remember them, and learne perfectly to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande them. Then, when we lye on our death bed, we ſhall not ſo much neede to be put in remembraunce. And if a man ready to die in time of neede (ſpecially if death come ſoudenly vpon him) confeſſe no more but the onely articles of our true and auncient faith, and Chriſtian religion, it were ſufficient, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialy if thoſe articles were holden and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by him that lyeth dying with a faithfull heart. For we hope, yea, we earneſtly beleeue, that our beloued anceſtors, in the great dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, though they knew nothing of the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods holy light and knowledge, and yet confeſſed and dyed in this Chriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and haue inioyed euerlaſting life: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall we beſtowe our poſsible diligence, to bring young children to be baptiſed, thoſe that be elder to be taught, and thoſe that bee at the point of death to be comforted, euery man according to his meaſure and gift, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (as much as lyeth in vs,) no body ſhall bee taken tarde, be vnprouided, or dye in his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13420:58"/> and vnbeleefe. But ſo to vſe our ſelues, that euery body may come vnto the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, be bleſſed, and ſaued, and ſo at the laſt, commend in our prayer euery man one with an other vnto God, which can migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tily bring to paſſe al that we deſire or require according to his power that worketh in vs. To him be prayſe in the congregation, which is in Chriſte Ieſus, for euer and euer. Amen.</head>
               <p>Laſt of all, now when the laſt pang commeth when the ſick body beginneth to ſcrocle and ſhrincke vp his bodie, as when one biteth vppon a ſowre apple, (as the biting of Adams apple teacheth vs: ſéeing the ſame bit and ſinne is runne ouer vs all, and therefore we all muſt raunſome it with our ſkinne and with death,) then may a man (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude) ſay to the ſicke as followeth: Lord into thy hand I commend my ſpirite. Almightie God lead thy ſoule into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting peace and bleſſedneſſe. And our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte raiſe vp againe, at the laſt day, this dead body to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting honour and glorie. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13420:59"/>
               <head>A ſhort exhortation to them that be preſent, and ſhall attend vppon the dead body.</head>
               <p>WElbeloued in our Lord, you haue nowe ſeene for a time the courſe of this departed bodie, and howe like a good Chriſtian and warriour, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of this life. Yea rather, howe fatherly and gratiouſly our Lord God hath viſited it, &amp; how at the laſt he hath deliuered it from al aduerſitie and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wherevnto the old Serpent of all mans progenie had brought vs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſéeing this dead perſon is ſo Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly departed out of this life full of miſerie, let vs, to the euerlaſting praiſe &amp; thankes of God, ſay ioyfully, <hi>We praiſe thee ô God, &amp;c.</hi> And to conclude, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly with all our heartes call vppon him, &amp; pray vnto him, that he wil vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n we ſhal be in extremitie and perill of death, gratiouſly, defende vs, and bleſſe vs, and giue vnto vs a bleſſed houre, thorough Chriſt his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne. Therefore wéepe not as the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13420:59"/> heathen and infidels, that beléeue not the reſurrection, and haue no hope ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon. For, <hi>If we beleeue</hi> (as witneſſeth S. Paule, 1. Theſſ. 4.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note>) <hi>that Ieſus died and is raiſed vp againe: likewiſe alſo ſhall God with him lead all thoſe that bee departed through Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heare may we ſée what it is to die well, namely the death of Chriſt that of neceſſitie died for vs wretched ſinners, whereby through his death he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, that we ſhal neuer die, but ſleepe only. Out of which ſléepe Chriſt a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lorde and king ſhall at the laſt day raiſe vs vp, if we beléeue vppon him, and lead vs with himſelfe into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting bliſſe and peace. Therefore, ſuffer this ſléeping bodie lie and reſt, and his ſoule in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane ſeaſon refreſh it ſelfe, and reioyce vntill that day, when body and ſoule ſhall come againe together, and enioy euerlaſting felicitie. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto our Lord Ieſus nowe helpe vs all together. Amen.</p>
               <p>Secondarily, it is not poſſible that man may ſo much bridle nature, that
<pb facs="tcp:13420:60"/> we ſhould not be heauie and complaine after the death of our friendes. And alſo Syrach ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cle. 38.</note> the 38. chapiter. <hi>My ſonne, powre foorth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eares ouer the dead, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to mourne as if thou haddeſt ſuffered great harme thy ſelfe, and then couer his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy according as he hath appointed, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect not his buriall. Make a greeuous la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and be earneſt in mourning, and vſe lamentation as he is worthie, and that a day or two, leaſt thou be euil ſpoken on, and then comfort thy ſelfe for thine heauineſſe. For of heauines commeth death, &amp; the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of the heart breaketh the ſtrength. Of the afflictions of the heart commeth ſorrow: and the life of him that is afflicted is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his heart. Take no heauines in heart, driue it away, and remember the laſt end. Forget it not, for there is no turning againe, thou ſhalt do him no good, but hurt thy ſelfe. Remember his iudgement, thine alſo ſhalbe likewiſe. Vnto me yeſterday, and vnto thee to day. Seeing the dead is at reſt, let his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance reſt, and comfort thy ſelfe againe for him, ſeeing his ſpirite is departed from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſée, that alſo the good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13420:60"/> and holy people haue after this maner mourned, as Abraham, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, Dauid, &amp;c. But at the length they haue layd mourning aſide, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues with the ioyefull reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: Yea, Chriſt himſelfe mourned for dead Lazarus. Iohn. 11.<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly and laſt of all, you ſhal wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfully bring this dead body to the earth, and ſhewe vppon it ſuch manner of worke of loue,<note place="margin">Eccle, 7.</note> as Syrach willeth vs in the vij. Chapter, ſaying, <hi>Shewe thy good will vpon the dead, ſpecially worſhipful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanie him, conuey him, and help him to his graue, for the reſurrection ſake.</hi> As Syrache alſo ſaith in the 38. Chapter,<note place="margin">Eccle. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>When any dyeth, burie him decently, and bring his body worſhipfully to the graue.</hi> As did good Tobie, Dauid, and many moe, to giue vs example how we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues towardes the dead.</p>
               <p>Our Lord God graunt vs his grace, that euery of vs, each one for other, may be diligent in this behalfe, whereby we all, to the prayſe of God, and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of our neighbours, without let or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb facs="tcp:13420:61"/> may begin, goe forward, and hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pily end through Chriſte our Lorde, in the holy Ghoſt. Amen.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſée, welbeloued in Chriſte our Lord, vpon this dead body, the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and high iudgement of GOD, and what an extreme horror our Lorde God hath vpon ſinne. For who hath thus iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this dead body, taken from him his comely countenaunce, giuen vnto him ſuch an ougly looke &amp; face? Onely death. But wherfore? Only bicauſe, <hi>Death is the wages for ſinne.</hi> But if this dead man ſince his birth had not ſinned, then had ſinne neuer had ſuche power ouer him. But from whence hath death this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer? Only from Gods wrath and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore tremble, looke vp to GOD, auoyde ſinne, for this dead body maye be a warning vnto you, that ye kéepe your ſelues from ſinne. Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus kéepe and defend vs altogether. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
               <p>FRiendly and Chriſtian Reader, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto haue ye perceiued in plaine &amp;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13420:61"/> ſimple manner, howe ſicke perſons are to be comforted, I haue alſo ſhortly ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed you, firſt of Repentaunce, then of Faith, and afterward of Good workes, which I haue not done only for the ſick, and for ſuch as be ready to dye, but alſo for them that be in health: to the intent that they that be whole, in the time of their proſperitie and good health, maye learne how to vſe and behaue them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and learne in time to dye. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more certeine then death, and nothing more vncerteine then to come vnto the right knowledge to dye. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought euery man before to prepare himſelfe, and to make ready to take this iourney in hand, and go forward, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may be carefull for that that will neceſſarily followe. But ſpecially ought we to remember theſe thinges before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually exerciſe our ſelues in the croſſe of warre, ſpecially nowe in the ſore daungerous warre againſt the cruell enimie of Chriſtendome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Turke,</hi> which if he haue the victorie, ſpareth no man, but without all mercy, heweth
<pb facs="tcp:13420:62"/> downe the miſerable Chriſtians, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them, and ſhooteth them through, where many times y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wounded bodies a long time lye in the gréene medowes, before they be brought into the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter houſe, in great daunger of deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if he were not before well prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and exerciſed in Gods worde. So that this ſouldier muſt fight with his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt the <hi>Turke,</hi> and with his ſoule againſt the Diuell him ſelfe. Howbeit, this ſhall be their comforte, out of the Prophet Daniel, the 7.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aniel. 7.</note> Chapter: That theſe murtherers of chriſtians &amp; bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houndes, doe onely by this meanes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Chriſtian ſoules, and doe further them to euerlaſting life. For he ſetteth him ſelfe with all his might, in greate force againſt the Saintes of God, and chiefly warreth againſt them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, without all queſtion, when ſo euer a Chriſtian man is ſlaine and ouercom by the <hi>Turke,</hi> yet dyeth he with a ſafe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in that that he is a Chriſtian: for he ſéeth, that this warre is againſt the Saintes of GOD, without cauſe.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13420:62"/> For the <hi>Turke</hi> hath no lawfull occaſion to fight againſt the Chriſtians, and ſo miſerably to ſpill Chriſtian bloud. Thus therfore dye they ſo much the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuller, ſéeing they go foorth in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their ſuperiours: and do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defend their owne countrie and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but alſo with their owne bloud, help to preſerue Chriſtian religion. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good Chriſtian, learne in time to dye, for thou knoweſt neither time nor houre, neither place nor manner, when, howe, either what maner of death thou ſhalt haue, ſpecially in this laſt and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous time. Therefore deferre not till the laſt puſhe, leaſt that you tarrie too long. Learne, learn this cunning while thou haſt time, memorie, and oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie therevnto. Then ſhall you go the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way, ſéeing the daye muſt néedes come, yeald thy ſelfe in time, with deſire and will therevnto, for it can not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded. Wherevnto our Lorde GOD giue vs grace, that we may well and happily depart. Amen.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, no man is to be tied and
<pb facs="tcp:13420:63"/> bound to vſe euery matter, as it is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteined, but if any other can or haue better, much good do it them: for I haue here remembred certeine tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wherein I my ſelfe like a poore, ſimple, plaine man, haue bene tempted and aſſaulted with, and haue experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, (if I may boaſt my ſelf of my weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe:) for I haue thriſe béene at that point, that euery man gaue me ouer, and deſpaired of my life in this worlde, yet at the laſt, our Lorde GOD by his great power reuiued me: wherefore I giue vnto him euerlaſting prayſe and thankes in Chriſt our Lorde. I will not ſay, that in my days I haue gone to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtian people, I haue comforted them, and haue bene at their end, whoſe names be written in the booke of life: where I haue experienced diuers and many temptations. GOD graunt both thée &amp; me his godly grace, that we may alſo bleſſedly ſléepe at the laſt in Chriſte our Lorde, and through Gods power at the laſt day, may be raiſed vp to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:13420:63"/>
               <head>How to aduiſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them that lye in priſon, and <hi>be by the Magistrate iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to dye.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſte welbeloued, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God giue you his grace, and true pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereby you may beare and patiently ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this your deſerued croſſe layde vpon you, ſéeing the matter is come thus far with you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the puniſhment of the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is falne vpon you, yeald your ſelf willingly therevnto, and thinke that this correction commeth from God him ſelfe. Therefore refuſe not the correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Almightie, as it is written in Iob the 5.<note place="margin">Iob. 5.</note> Séeing then that euery mans iudgement commeth from God our Lord, as it is in Solomon, the 29. of his Prouerbes,<note place="margin">Prou. 29.</note> receiue ſuch iudgement and puniſhment vp from our Lord God as a fatherly correction, as the Epiſtle
<pb facs="tcp:13420:64"/> to the Hebrues witneſſeth, Chapter 12. where the text ſaith thus,<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſonn, make not light of the correction of the Lorde, and despaire not when thou art puniſhed by him. For the Lord doth correct him whom he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and he beateth euery ſonne which he taketh to him ſelfe.</hi> And ſo it commeth to paſſe,<note place="margin">Cant. 8.</note> as Solomon ſaith in his highe ſong, the 8. Chapter, that the loue which the Lorde beareth vs, is as ſtrong as death. It appeareth vnto the world, as though the loue of God were very miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, death, and deſtruction. Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, there is vnder ſuch loue, great mercy, goodneſſe, life, and bleſſedneſſe hidden. For, <hi>If we be iudged, we be corrected by the Lorde, to the intent that we ſhould not be damned with the world,</hi> as ſaith S. Paule in the firſt epiſt. to the Corinthians, the 10.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 10.</note> Chap. Therefore, learne here with ſpirituall eyes to beholde, that you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der puniſhment may ſée grace, vnder correction peace, and vnder death life. Thus ſhal not this croſſe layd vpon you be very ſore and fearfull, but you may beare it, and you alſo ſhal patiently ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13420:64"/> it. For God can ſoone end this croſſe, that you ſhall be able to carrie it. For as much then, as <hi>God our Lorde hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to euery man a certeine end of his life, which he ſhall not paſſe.</hi> Iob. 14.<note place="margin">Iob. 14.</note> thinke you nowe that your appointed time by God is nowe come, and this day is by God appointed vnto you, for a certeine end of your life. Trouble not your ſelfe much therefore, after what maner you haue taken your life from God, and that you ſhall ſo ſoone deliuer it him againe. But ſet your will to Gods will, and ſay, Father thy will be done, and not mine, if it be thy pleaſure that I ſhall drinke this cuppe which thou haſt filled for me, giue me thy grace thervnto, that I may continue in a true Chriſtian belefe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mine end, and that I may vnder this my croſſe and ſuffering, in perfect pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, paſſe through it to euerlaſting life. Amen.</p>
               <p>Secondarily, For as muche as you haue now heard, that this croſſe and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment commeth from God him ſelfe, and is laide vpon you by God, through
<pb facs="tcp:13420:65"/> an ordinarie magiſtrate, you ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand nowe further, well learne to knowe the great and earneſt anger of God ouer ſinne: for it is no ſmal matter before God, when a man behaueth him ſelfe contrarie to Gods lawe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually without ceaſing, offendeth and prouoketh God, with his vnpenitent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. GOD is very angrie with ſuche déedes, and is muche offended againſt ſinne, not only with temporall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but alſo with euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>Therefore, you ſhall vnderſtande, well knowe, and learne, that you by meanes of your doings and ſinne, haue wrought and deſerued, not only a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, but alſo an euerlaſting death. For if God would deale with you, acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his earneſt and vttermoſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then ſhould your puniſhment be euerlaſting, and neuer haue end. But ſéeing that God hath forſéene you from the beginning, and hath taken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued you through his fatherly correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the time of grace, but ſpecially nowe at this time, he will turne your
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13420:65"/> euerlaſting puniſhment into temporal puniſhment: cut ſhort his euerlaſting anger and diſpleaſure, to a timely and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral anger. And yet the ſame before him is no anger, but a fatherly viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby he will make you leape o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the way to euerlaſting damnation, and lead you out of it, and by this croſſe he will bring you to the right way to heauen. Therefore, our Lord GOD of grace and fauour, by meanes of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent death of his welbeloued ſonne our Lord Chriſt, will take from you the euerlaſting puniſhment, and take the ſame from your ſoule, and lay it vppon your body, ſo that both your body and your ſoule may at the length be made frée, and deliuered wholy, both from worldly and euerlaſting puniſhment. Therfore this worldly correction is laid vpon the body, but as it were the ſpace of the twinckling of an eye, whereby you being warned of your vnpenitent life, might leaue off to ſin, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will not be, and you would ſtill haue continued in ſinne, and thereby at
<pb facs="tcp:13420:66"/> the laſt, haue fallen into the feareful an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God, and euerlaſting torment &amp; plague. Howbeit, God of his great mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, hath taken mercy of your fall, and will deliuer you from his great, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſtrong, and euerlaſting iudgement. The righteouſneſſe and iuſtice of God hath earneſtly ſought, and required, to haue her right vpon you, that is to ſay, euerlaſting puniſhment and paine: but the mercy of God hath on your behalfe ſtept in the middle, and hath foughten againſt iudgement, and mercy hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined the victorie, and driuen iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment backe, ſo that ſhe ſhal neuer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after lay any thing to your charge: how be it ſo, that righteouſneſſe is partly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréed with all and ſatiſfied, but onely temporally, as farre as concerneth the body, but not the ſoule. This is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull battel, and on your ſide maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly brought aboute, through grace. For what is this temporal &amp; tranſitorie ſuffering, enduring (as it were) but the twinckling of an eye, in compariſon of the euerlaſting tormentes, where you
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13420:66"/> ſhould haue abidden the euerlaſting death and paine. Therefore is this a tollerable, yea rather an acceptable and pleaſaunt exchaunge, ſéeing we, by our ſinne, haue deſerued the euerlaſting wrath of God &amp; puniſhment, that this puniſhment now ſhall endure but for a time, yea rather but the twinkling of an eye, which elſe ſhould haue béene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting and fearefull, if God in his anger would haue delt with vs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nowe welbeloued, you ſhall doe like one that hath his houſe a fire, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all in a flame, ſo that it is vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be quenched: Then wil he throwe out, and fetche from thence all his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; iewels: And if he can ſaue them from burning, he may with them build vp an other houſe. Thus muſt you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe do. Your houſe, I meane your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is of a light flame, it ſo burneth with ſinne, that there is no hope to quench it, you muſt now let your old houſe burne, and now looke about and bethinke you, howe to ſaue and deliuer your treaſure and iewels, that is, your ſoule, through
<pb facs="tcp:13420:67"/> a true faith in Chriſt your deliuerer, &amp; then ſhall you wel at Doomes day, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough that iewel, come to a new houſe, where you ſhal haue a new bodie in the bleſſed reſurrection of the elected and choſen people of God: which neuer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, nor thorough fire can be conſumed. But you ſhal then haue ſuch a bodie, as ſhal neuer die, nor at any time ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny griefe, puniſhment, paine, harts ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, trouble or néed, neuermore forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but enioye euerlaſting peace and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes. Therefore praye now, that he wil rule and turne the harts of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, that they will lay vpon you, of fauour, ſuch correction, as ſhalbe moſt ſéemely in this caſe, that you may quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer and beare. For, God ruleth the heartes of the magiſtrates, and ſitteth amongſt them in their counſel &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And ſéeing the great magiſtrate is of your ſide, you haue altogether, and can lacke nothing.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, marke alſo further (welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) that <hi>Gods iudgement euer begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at his owne children.</hi> For, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13420:67"/> he purpoſeth to correcte the world with his diſpleaſure, and earneſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, firſt of all he ſéeketh out his owne, and viſiteth them, and correcteth them firſt of all with his fatherly rodde, whereby he may ſaue and deliuer them from the endleſſe and euerlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> as S. Peter ſheweth in his firſt Epiſtle and 4 Chap. out of the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ieremie in the 25. Chapter,<note place="margin">Iere. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>The iudgement of God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>beginneth at Gods houſe.</hi> And as Dauid ſaith, Pſa. 75.<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord hath a cuppe in his hand, which is full of mightie wine, he skinketh, and filleth out of it. But godleſſe people muſt drincke all out, and make a carrouſe, and ſuppe vppe the very dregges of Gods wrath.</hi> It is hereby ment, GOD giueth euery bodie their meaſure, that they ſhal ſuffer: but the grounds and dregges remaine for the vngodly, eſpecially for the ſtubborne, froward, and vnpenitent world, which will néedes periſhe in their ſtubbornes. But the iudgement, anger, correction, and viſitation, which God of his grace layeth vppon his children, is after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:13420:68"/> ſortes. God correcteth ſome of his children with ſicknes, ſome with pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſome with impriſonment, ſome with contempt, that they be not regarded nor any accompt made of them, ſome other with temporal death by the magiſtrate, as he hath now purpoſed to correct you: therefore it appeareth outwardly, that God ſheweth himſelfe as thoughe he were angrie with you. But, <hi>With him there is no anger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſaie. 54.</note> 
                  <hi>for his anger lasteth but the twinkling of an eye, after that he taketh vppe his againe with euerlaſting grace and mercie.</hi> As the prophet Eſaias in his 54. Chapter ſaith. And as Dauid remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth in his 89. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note> 
                  <hi>If the children of grace breake and forſake Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and keepe not Gods lawes, then will God with his rodde ſeuerely viſite them: But hee will not turne his grace from them.</hi> The cauſe is, the mercifull couenaunt which God hath, by meanes of his onely begotten ſonne, made and eſtabliſhed with his children.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, thus you ſhall earneſtly beléeue, that this your ſuffering, care,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13420:68"/> ſhame, martyrdome, and death, is not ſufficient, thereby to purchaſe euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life. For, if you by your death and paines, might (before God) do penance, and ſatiſfie, then dyed our Lord Chriſte in vaine: but ſéeing he dyed, he hath by that his ſuffering, paſſion, and death, done ſufficient penance for your ſinnes, appeaſed Gods wrath, reconciled you to GOD his father, and purchaſed for you euerlaſting righteouſnes &amp; bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therefore by this your ſuffering &amp; death, you can not eſcape Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor make amendes to Gods iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, nor make ſatiſfaction for euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting puniſhment, but only thereby you do make ſatiſfaction before the worlde. For ſéeing that you haue done amiſſe, &amp; offended the outwarde, temporall, and worldly iuſtice, and tranſgreſſed, and found guiltie thereof, you muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſatiſfie the ſame externall and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward iuſtice, with ſuch outward puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the worlde and the magiſtrate can doe: for aboue that, the world nor the magiſtrate can not reach, nor giue
<pb facs="tcp:13420:69"/> correction. But for as much as the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whiche you haue committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Magiſtrate, is alſo againſt God, and his holy commaundementes, ſpecially this ſinne, whiche you at the firſt on the racke, or pyning banke, and after by your owne confeſſion haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, beſides other grieuous faultes, wherewith in your life time, from your youth hitherto, you haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God your Lord, in ſuch manner, that he might puniſh you for ſuch offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces euerlaſtingly, and not for a time, yet will he not do ſo, as I haue told you before, but he will mercifully forgiue you ſuch offences altogether, both ſmall and great, howe ſo euer you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them, through the deſeruing, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, ſhame, &amp; bitter death of his deare ſonne our Lord Chriſt Ieſus, your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. So that Gods iuſtice is ſatiſfied for you by Chriſt our Lord. For, <hi>GOD hath made his ſonn for our ſakes, to be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, holineſſe, and our deliuerer.</hi> 1. Cor. 1.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 1.</note> Therfore you muſt beleue this, &amp; not doubt, &amp; confeſſe it with your mouth. Do
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13420:69"/> you beléeue this deare beloued? Say yea.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, leſt peraduenture you ſhould imagine and ſay, How commeth it then to paſſe, that God hath only laide vpon me this ſhame, reproch, &amp; death? Howe commeth it to paſſe, that he hath ſpyed me out only? Am I then alone, the moſt wicked, the moſt vnhappie man vppon the earth? There be yet many worſe then I. Why could he not viſite and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me after ſome other faſhion? Marke wel here and learne, that it becommeth you not to murmur and be vnpatient, (by your leue) againſt God, nor his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed worke: for if God will thus viſite you, you ought not to weiue it, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it: for God can beſt ſkill, according to his fatherly goodneſſe, how to intreate and handle his children, and he will not deale alike with one childe as with an other. He hath many croſſes and rodds, whereby he will chaſtice his. He forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſome long, and another he patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abideth, he leadeth him therby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: the thirde he taketh foorth to him ſelfe with this rod, but he taketh vp
<pb facs="tcp:13420:70"/> an other with an other rod, after them our Lorde God layeth vpon euery one his croſſe. Therfore (by your leaue) you ſhall not deſpaire nor doubt, neither wiſhe nor deſire that you were dead, or that this or that carrie you away, as ſome haue done, of impatience, feare, and ſhame of the world. What hurt is it to you, that you muſt (in déede) be ſhamed before the worlde, and that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man beholdeth you, as vppon a great offender, ſéeing neuertheleſſe that you be the child of God, through your beléefe vpon Chriſt? Which our Lord God, and the whole armie and hoaſt of heauen doth nowe heholde, &amp; looke vpon, though it doth not apeare before the world. All that you haue to doe, ſhal paſſe away in the twinckling of an eye: after that the worlde ſhall beholde you after an other faſhion, I mean, at doomes day, in great ioy and glory, as one of Gods choſen children. What ſhal it then hinder you, though you for an hour or two, muſt be kept to be ſhamed, and openly executed or put to death? Reioyce, be frolike, that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13420:70"/> at the general day thou ſhalt eſcape con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, before the whole earth, and all the hoaſt and armie of heauen. It is much better, that you ſhould ſuffer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch and ſhame a little while, before a ſmal number, then that at that day, you ſhoulde be ſhamed and confounded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Angels and the whole worlde, for euer and euer. Therfore yeald your ſelf thervnto willingly, and behold this ſhame &amp; death, not with your bodily eye but with your ſpirituall eye. Doe away your eyes, remembraunce, and reaſon: let euery man laughe, mocke, looke, ſay, and doe what they will. Looke not vpon man, but vpon God, he is at hand with all Angels, they behold you gratiouſly, they haue pitifull hearts with you, and our Lord Chriſt, and our deliuerer will take you with him into euerlaſting peace and bleſſedneſſe. There be alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong this companie, heape, and cluſter of people, many good men that feare God, that be very ſorrie, and take griefe with you, and doe truly pray to God for you. Therefore do you not ſuffer alone,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:71"/> but Chriſt our Lord and head ſuffereth with you. Likewiſe, al Chriſtian mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſuffer with you: likewiſe all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures beholde with you, and heartily long for your deliuerie, as witneſſeth Saint Paule, Rom. 8.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. 8.</note> Therefore turne you to him that ſtriketh you, that is, to God your true louing father, and praye vnto him, that he will mitigate, ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and eaſe your paines and ſmartes, and lend vnto you a ſtrong and merrie heart, manfully and patiently to beare this croſſe laide vpon you, and to ſtande vpright: And then you ſhall proue in the midſt of your trouble, that he is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully on your ſide, &amp; doth helpe you, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and beareth your croſſe; for he will be with you in your aduerſitie: therfore lay al your trouble only vpon our Lord God, he wil firſt make your troubles in your heart and conſcience eaſier, and take them cleane away. And after that your heart is once at peace with God, and that you haue obteined a quiet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, then will all bodily paines be very little, and nothing in compariſon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13420:71"/> of the conſcience. Then, ſéeing that to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man particularly, or by him ſelfe, death as a iuſt rewarde of ſinne is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and that we all which ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main after you, muſt alſo get vs hence, and no man remaine, but that death muſt ſwallowe vppe the whole worlde: what hurt is it to you, that you go a litle before vs, to the way of bleſſedneſſe, and haue poſſeſſed and inioyed euerlaſting life before vs? Though you nowe by the way to bleſſedneſſe, ſhall tread a hard, bitter, ſharpe, and rough way, yet haue you this aduantage, that you in a whole body, and good memorie, and perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſlide hence: and in death, you doe thruſt into euerlaſting life, and all we muſt come after. And who can tell, how we, poore, néedie, and forſaken men ſhal doe, and what ſhall come of vs? We be ſure to be aſſaulted with many miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes and plagues and at the laſt, ſome long time lye ſtretching, and ſuffer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſmarts and troubles vpon our ſicke bed, all which you haue eſcaped, and in the meane ſeaſon reſt quietly, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:13420:72"/> your ſelfe, and inioy euerlaſting peace and happineſſe.</p>
               <p>Sixtely, Nowe welbeloued, while you be in the way to the kingdome of heauen, and that you will euen now go thither: it is good for you to knowe the way, and diligently to learne it, and to inquire after it, leaſt you wander, or be lead or driuen from it. Therfore learne well to lay hande and holdfaſt vpon the ladder to heauen, which ladder the good Patriarch Iaacob did ſée, Gen. 8.<note place="margin">Gen. 8.</note> That is the ladder whereby the Angels clime vp and downe vppon, whiche from the earth with his top, reacheth vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, wherevpon at the vppermoſt part our Lord God ſtandeth. Chriſt him ſelfe is this ladder, Iohn. 1.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 1.</note> Therefore holde faſt by true faith vpon this ladder, for, <hi>No man can go to heauen, but he that came from thence, that is, the ſonne of man which is in heauen.</hi> This Lord is the very lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to heauen. For by his manhoode he ſtandeth vppon the earth, and with his godhead he reacheth to heauen, where God him ſelfe doth appeare. If you will
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13420:72"/> goe to heauen, you muſt begin at Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes humanitie to clime vp, ſpecially through his paſſion and death, and to ſéeke after his very godhead aboue, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the top of the ladder, where God him ſelfe is, and ſay thus. My Lorde and my God, for as much as I muſt goe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as I am very willing, and euen now haue begunne, be thou my ladder, leader, and guide, for thou art the very way to heauen. Iohn. 14.<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> And no man commeth to the father but through thée, and by thée, as thou thy ſelfe doeſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Iohn. 10.<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> where thou ſayeſt thus, <hi>I am the doore, if any man enter in by me, hee ſhall bee ſafe.</hi> Thus ſhall you, vnto the right way to heauen, prepare and dreſſe your ſelfe: for Chriſt is the onely gate into heauen. Heauen it ſelfe is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wide and large, but it hath but only one gate, through the which a man may come, but as ſoone as you haue gotten this gate, and gotten through it, then haue you left behinde you (as it were in a heape) al miſfortune at once, and then are you aſſured and defended by this
<pb facs="tcp:13420:73"/> gate, that no aduerſitie hereafter for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer can hurt you. There do you lay at once at your backe, death, ſinne, diuell, hell, and all that can be againſt you. There be you then ſure and ſafe as in a ſtrong caſtel, that no man can any more ſtirre vp hurt againſt you. Therefore, let no man withdrawe you from this way, goe vnto it boldly, you ſhall come ſafe from thence to the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; thither ſhal the good angels be your guides, that harme can not once touche you. Be therefore of good courage, our Lord Chriſte is your king, which hath dyed before you, &amp; hath made the pathe plaine, and ſufficiently ſtrengthened and made ſafe this iourney: therefore go ſtreight foorth, &amp; hold right on in this way, turne of no ſide, for, <hi>You ſhall ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goe on the right hande, nor of the left,</hi> as our Lord God doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund, Deut. 12.<note place="margin">Deut. 12.</note> You take the left hande, out of the right way, when you deſpaire of Gods mercy, where God is before you. And on the right hand you go out of the way too wide, when you truſt in your worke,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13420:73"/> death, paſſion, and ſhame: therfore abide in the middle way toward heauen, and then ſhall you not goe out of the way. Vpon this way ſhall you vndoubtedly finde the true life, for our Lord Chriſte is not onely the way, but alſo the life, ſo that you ſhall receiue in Chriſt the true life, as he ſaith, and witneſſeth of him ſelfe, Iohn. 11.<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>I am</hi> (ſaith Chriſte) <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and the life,</hi> but not only the life for him ſelfe, but ſuche a life, as giueth the right life, and diuideth it among all them that put their truſt vpon Chriſte. For, Chriſt ſaith further alſo, <hi>Whoſoeuer beleeueth on me, he ſhall liue, though he be dead.</hi> Suche a valiaunt and almightie thing is it about faith, and about all the faithfull of Chriſte, that they lay hande vpon life in the middeſt of death, that they ſing merrily, <hi>In the middest of death we be in life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Welbeloued, you muſt vnfeignedly beléeue al this, that it is no ſport nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite that Chriſt ſaith and promiſeth: for he is the trueth it ſelfe, his wordes be true and certeine, therevpon ſhall you
<pb facs="tcp:13420:74"/> haue no manner of doubt, for the truth it ſelfe doeth ſay, <hi>I am the way, and the trueth, and the life, and alſo the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Whoſoeuer beléeueth truely vpon him, he receiueth in the midſt of death the reſurrection, ſo that nowe you ſhall lye the twinckling of an eye in death, &amp; ſlide thence to life. But by this death, through Chriſt, you ſhall inioy euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſurrection, where you ſhal neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more dy. Theſe be vnſpeakable words, and aboue meaſure comfortable, grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wordes, that a wretched ſinner on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through beléefe in Chriſte, ſhall finde life in death, in dying reſurrection, and in the middeſt of the dongeon of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall find the right way to heauen. Therefore be of good comforte before death, ſéeing that God is ſuch a mightie Lorde, that bringeth vnto you out of death life, and bringeth you through the ſnares of death, to euerlaſting peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> quietnes. God graunt you this. Amen</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, Welbeloued, for as muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as you be nowe, through faith, a mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, the olde ſerpent will now
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13420:74"/> ſet vppon you: and as he hath bitten Chriſte our head in the héele, ſo will he a little whip your héele, for that you are kept here and muſt dy, that is his ſtroke and byte, yea, the poyſon wherby the old ſerpent hath ſtinged and poyſoned you. Howbeit, it is nothing elſe but a byting by the héele, that can do you no hurt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the right life. She biteth the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God after many ways, but they againe treade vpon the olde ſerpentes head, through our Lord Chriſte, in that that they through beléefe, as through the right Triacle and medicin, driue away, heale, and quenche the ſtripe, the biting, and the poyſon of the ſerpent. Therfore valiantly tread down the ſerpents head in thy Lord Chriſt, through a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian beléefe, on the gratious promiſe of God, that Chriſte is the onely head of Chriſtendome, which firſt of al with his paſſion, death, and ioyfull reſurrection, ouercame ſathan, and brake the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head. The dragons head is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, ſpecially ſinne, death, and hell. There hath the old ſerpent opened his
<pb facs="tcp:13420:75"/> iawes, &amp; would ſwalow vs vp in ſinne, death, &amp; hel. But our louing lord Chriſt hath broken the ſerpents ſcull, ſo that ſhe is not able anymore to gape againſt the faithfull, that ſhe may ſwalow them vppe, as ſhe hath purpoſed. Therefore learne nowe, howe you ſhall trouble, charme, coniure, and ban or curſe this ſerpent, ſo that ſhe ſhall not hurte you, which you ſhall do, if you ouercome her through beléefe in Chriſt, and ſo ſhal you treade vpon her head.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, Although my welbeloued, your wife, children, brother, ſiſter, and your friends, may tempt you, that they ſhall nowe be in néede, and muſt ſuffer for your miſdéedes, let goe and let paſſe altogether all ſuch thoughts, and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly temptations, and thinke thus: Well now, albeit that I hitherto haue béene by God appointed, and ſet to be a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyor to take care, &amp; to mainteine my wife, children, &amp;c. and I haue not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly behaued my ſelfe in that calling, I hartily therfore deſire my Lord God, in Chriſte Ieſus my deliuerer, that he
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13420:75"/> will not lay to my charge that ſinne, but through grace pardon me: for I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſorie. Therefore almightie God, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou wilt take that my care and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from me, and put me beſides it, I commend them vnto thée, as to the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt magiſtrate, &amp; their Lorde, defender, &amp; father, that thou wilt vouchſafe that I maye commende vnto thée my wife, children and friendes, and not to ſuffer that they ſhalbe charged with mine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, but to take care for them, defend them, féede them and mainteine them, as the true onely father in heauen and earth. And that thou wilt vouchſafe, in my ſtéed, to ſend them ſome other, that may leade them, and bring them vp in godly feare, and Chriſtianlike conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. And althoughe that they, before the world, muſt be charged with my faultes, that thou wilt richly requite thoſe things vnto them, and lay againſt that, thy gentle, gratious, and fatherly bleſſing, ſo that they may enioye their innocencie. All theſe thinges I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend vnto thée together, Oh moſt mightie
<pb facs="tcp:13420:76"/> Lord and God, into thy gratious hand. Wherevnto alſo I commit my life and ſoule. Therefore doe I yéeld vnto thy mercie altogether, and in perfect truſt &amp; bleſſed hope, that thou wilt gratiouſly accept this my poore prayer, &amp; heare me in Ieſu Chriſt thine only louing ſonne. Amen.</p>
               <p>Now welbeloued in this ouergiuing and prayer, wherein you haue giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer al things vnto God in your prayer, and offered them vp, you ſhall wholy &amp; throughly perſuade your ſelfe of Gods mercie. For, <hi>God is rich toward them that call vppon him.</hi> Beléeue this thing onely, and ſo it will in déede come to paſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the comfortable promiſe of Chriſt our Lord, in the 11. of Marke (where he comforteth ſuch as doe pray, and promiſeth to giue them all.) Oure Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Whatſoeuer you pray for in your prayer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marke. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>onely beleeue that ye ſhall receiue it, and you ſhall haue it.</hi> And in Marke the 9.<note place="margin">Marke. 9.</note> Chriſt ſaith thus, <hi>If you can beleeue, all thinges are poſſible to them that beleeue.</hi> Therefore giue vnto our Lord
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13420:76"/> God the glorie, and eſtéeme him to be a true God. Then will he for his trueth ſake heare your prayer and kéepe you: For, <hi>He is gratious and mercifull, of great goodnes &amp; trueth. God ſurely is the higheſt, but he looketh vppon the loweſt very gladly, and of them that be of gentle and courteous minde and heart.</hi> Onely for his loue ſake, that he beareth towardes them that be of troubled and heauie hearts. For they be ſo commended vnto him, that he hath ſpecial regard vpon them. As our Lord God himſelfe acknowledgeth, Eſaie 66.<note place="margin">Eſaie. 66.</note> where God ſaith thus, <hi>I behold ſuch as be in miſerie, and haue a contrite heart, and on ſuch as feare my word.</hi> This is the right offering, that pleaſeth God, ſpecially a troubled ſpirit. For, <hi>A ſorrowful &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled heart will not God deſpiſe.</hi> Pſalm. 51.<note place="margin">Pſalme 51.</note> If you then can commend all your cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to God, your very creatour, &amp; giue ouer all to him, then will he doe like a louing and gentle father, &amp; can well tell how to prouide for all yours. For, <hi>he is the Iudge of the widowes, and the father of orphanes and the fatherleſſe.</hi> As vpon him
<pb facs="tcp:13420:77"/> it is written in the Pſalme. 68.<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Then, ſéeing that God by this means and croſſe layd vppon you, wil take you away from yours, you ſhall not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſorrowe, nor be diſmayde, ſpecially ſéeing that within a ſhort time, you ſhal finde againe all your friends in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, euen as you beléeue the ioyful reſurrection of all Chriſtians, to enioy euerlaſting liuing. There ſhall you find for your earthly friendes, heauenly friendes. To die you muſt neceſſarily, and prepare your ſelfe therevnto, as all mankinde muſt, and no man be left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde. God doth this thing vnto you for the beſt, bycauſe this way he doth ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten your griefes and pains, helpeth you this way through all paine, ſhame, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and death, very eaſily and fatherly. Therfore be luſtie and of good courage, he that layeth this croſſe vpon you, he will alſo helpe you to beare it, giue you patience, &amp; make a bleſſed end of it.</p>
               <p>Ninethly, Séeing then that God hath laid this croſſe vpon you, that you ſhuld heare it a very litle while, therefore you
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13420:77"/> ſhall not excuſe your ſelfe, nor make your fault light to the world, nor ſmooth it, as though you were guiltleſſe, or as though you had not deſerued this your puniſhment laide vpon you. Take not the figge leafe before thée, thereby to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thine offence, as the nature of olde Adam is to doe, and as Adam after his ſinne would thereby haue couered him ſelfe. But giue God the glorie, as Ioſua warned the offender Achan, when he tooke him with the things that were cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, Ioſua. 7.<note place="margin">Ioſ. 7.</note> Then ſaid Ioſua there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>My ſonne, giue to the Lord God of Iſrael the glory, and giue him the prayſe, and tell me and confeſſe what hast thou done, &amp; lye not.</hi> Then alſo ſaid Achan therevpon, <hi>Surely I haue ſinned against the Lorde the God of Iſrael, thus &amp; thus haue I done, &amp;c.</hi> There did Achan before all folke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his offence: and albeit he were by the Magiſtrate condemned to dye by Gods appointment, yet is he (no doubt thereof) taken vp through Gods mercy, and much commended for his confeſſion, he gaue God the glory, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13420:78"/> departed in Gods mercy. Likewiſe wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued, ſhall you alſo doe, ſearche your heart, giue God the glorie, which alonly is good, wiſe, righteous, and holy, but all men be euill and falſe. Take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hence with you, carrie nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye with you, but ſearche your heart and conſcience, and what you haue don, denie it not, do not make it leſſe: but ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is manifeſt and knowne, and ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing GOD hath brought your offence to light, and by the magiſtrate ordeined will puniſh you: therefore giue God prayſe and thanks, that he will of grace not puniſhe you for euer. Thinke it is much better here, before fewe folke, to be a little while ſhamed, then hereafter before al the world, and the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of heauen: for all muſt come to light, and be openly knowne, therefore it is much better here then there. Then ſéeing that God by the Magiſtrate, hath made it knowne, therefore ſuffer it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently &amp; willingly, and blame no man, as though any man had opened it of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or condemned you as your enimie.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13420:78"/> The Magiſtrates iudgement is Gods iudgement, and the ſentence hath alſo pleaſed him. He is the higheſt Iudge, therefore blame no man, and charge no man that is vnguiltie in this caſe. If you haue at any time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed any thing to charge the innocent, whereby you might cleare your ſelfe, or thereby to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape and be at libertie, then burthen not your ſelfe therewith, nor let your ſoule carrie any ſuch thing away, but excuſe the innocent, and pray to God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that he will pardon you, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your heart to be bent to any vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way, to excuſe your offence, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it. But before God confeſſe it, aſke grace, and ſéeing it is come to light, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it before the whole worlde, or elſe you ſtriue againſt Gods iudgement, his will &amp; his worke, which ſurely is horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, from which our Lord defend you, of his grace, through Chriſt Ieſus his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued ſonne in the holy Ghoſt. Amen.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, I further alſo charge you, my deare friend, that from the bottome of your hart, you wil reconcile, forgiue,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:79"/> and forget all men that haue done any thing againſt you, either by worde or déede, whether it be for this matter, or for any other before. If you haue by any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bene hurted or harmed, though they be guiltie of this your iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſuffring, and death, either if they haue eſpyed, or laid hand vpon you, al this together ſhal you caſt out of your heart, and lay aſide all maner of ſwelling, ſnarling, malice, hatred, enimitie, and euill will: and contrarie ſhewe a gentle heart, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue, and gentle ſpeach, without all hatred, bitterneſſe, and euill will, as a patient lamb, as Chriſt our Lord, which was altogether innocent, yet vpon the croſſe prayed for his enimies, and ſaid, <hi>Father, forgiue them, for they knowe not what they doe.</hi> Thus ſhall you likewiſe do and thinke: Well, now welbeloued Lord and father, though I be not guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and innocent, as thy welbeloued ſonne, but haue worthily deſerued all puniſhment, wrath, and vengeaunce: Likewiſe, ſéeing thou of frée grace and mercy through Ieſus Chriſte, haſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13420:79"/> pardoned me, &amp; after my departure wilt neuermore reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber my ſin: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I require thée, that thou wilt giue vnto me ſuch a gentle, friendly, &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hart through thy holy ſpirit, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may forgiue, and forget, and alſo reconcile my ſelfe vnto euery man, as well friendes as foes: for thou wilt alſo forgiue me, yea, thou haſt already clearly forgiuen all my ſins &amp; miſdéeds. And for better aſſurance hereof, giue me grace, might, and ſuche a burning charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward my neighbours, that I may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue euery man, and that from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my heart: So ſhall I be ſure, that thou haſt forgotten and forgiuen me, and at the laſt day, this ſhall be the ſigne, that is, the Chriſtian and brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue, that we alſo be thy diſciples, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we doe ſhewe Chriſtian loue one toward an other. Kéepe in me alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gratious promiſe of Chriſte my louing Lorde, that ſaith thus, Matth. 6.<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>When you forgiue men their faultes, then will alſo my heauenlie father forgiue you your faults.</hi> With theſe Chriſtian comforts I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:13420:80"/> my ſelfe, and ſtay my ſelfe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon thy mercifull promiſe. Doe with me after thy godly ſaying and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for thou doeſt require of me that I be merciful, as thou alſo art merciful towards vs. Therfore I do knowe, that in this my departure to death, there is no better, nor more acceptable offering, then that I ſhould ſhewe charitie, and of mercy with well vnto all men, pray for all men, intreat and do well vnto al men, as much as is poſſible for me. For <hi>God hath pleaſure in mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſee 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and not in offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</hi> Oſée. 6.</p>
               <p>Twelfthly, You haue alſo welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for a comfortable example, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> théefe which alſo had done very wickedly, for whiche he alſo receiued puniſhment of the magiſtrate, but this puniſhment was vnto him onely the cauſe and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theraunce, that he did not onely knowe GOD, and was faithfull, but was alſo hanged beſide Chriſte his ſaluation: whereby he conceiued ſpeciall comfort, that Chriſt the innocent Lorde woulde pitie his miſerie, and would forgiue him
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13420:80"/> all his ſinnes and wickedneſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto otherwiſe he ſhoulde neuer haue forſaken his naughtie life, but woulde haue continued in his wickednes, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneſſe, and vſed his ſtiffneſſe and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie his whole life long, without al repentance, &amp; turning from his naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie liuing.</p>
               <p>And ſo peraduenture had it ben with you, you would haue gone forwarde in your vnrighteouſneſſe, therein abiden, withered, and ſtarued for euer, without al penance, or repentance, godly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, vnder the feareful anger of God, being bound with Gods iudgement, &amp; condemnation. Therefore, ſéeing that God hath deliuered you from this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable blindneſſe and error, he ſhall from hencefoorth leade you by this occaſion, means, and purpoſe, firſt bring you to know your ſelfe, &amp; bring you to true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, &amp; penance, ſuffer godly know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge to light in your hart, kéepe you in the true faith of Chriſte Ieſu, and will ſuffer you to depart in the ſame at the laſt without all doubt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13420:81"/>
               <p>Behold now, dearely beloued, howe our Lorde God, is a valiant almightie father, that of al naughtineſſe can make all goodneſſe, and will to his turne all worſt thinges to the beſt. Sathan had thought that through this your fall, and miſdéede, he would for euer haue kept you in his kingdome, and to haue made you a member of himſelfe. But our lord God commeth, and bringeth to paſſe by this means and croſſe, that he hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and hindered all ſathans purpoſe. Sathan thought he had made all cocke ſure with you, and had brought you to euerlaſting ſinne and ſhame, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to haue kept you continually there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. But God commeth, and turneth the leafe vp, and maketh of you that were the childe of darkeneſſe, the childe of light, and of euerlaſting bliſſe. Amen.</p>
               <p>Twelftly, Nowe deare friende, I warne you nowe (at the laſt) that you will depart hence to death without all feare, nor be not diſmaide of death, by reaſon of your ſinne. But herein take héede, that thou do not alonly looke vpon
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13420:81"/> death vnder the eyes, and doeſt wreſtle with him, but take thine almightie god with thée, which hath before laide hand vppon death, and hath ouercome him, that is, Ieſus Chriſt thy Lord and king, which in the garden ſo mightily wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſinne and death, that bloudie ſweat dropped from him, Matth. 26.<note place="margin">Matth 26.</note> therefore weigh it not. And againe, be not afraide of death, ſéeing you meete with him, with this king and Lord, but you ſhall do thus to him, ſet all your on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfort, hope, and aſſurance, vppon your Chriſte, that hath made your way for you, broken the hedge, and kéepeth the field, and hath for you ouerthrowne the mightie Goliah, and hath brought the bleſſed victorie home to your doore, as I haue before this time ſhewed you, and yet againe muſt ſette before your face. For nowe is the time, ſeeing you are come to the very puſh, and this your daungerous enimie (that is very terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto the whole worlde) will ſtande chiefly with you, to bring and driue you from this point, and ſo lay hande vpon
<pb facs="tcp:13420:82"/> you. Therfore take to yourſelfe the true ſhielde, which is Chriſte your defence, whome you ſhall ſet againſt death. For death hath layde hand vpon this inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Lord, and wearied him without al right and equitie, whereby death euen loſt al his ſtrength and might, ſo that he can do no more, when this Lord laieth hand vpon him, and taketh to him ſelfe thoſe that be his. Therefore be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide, for, <hi>Death is ſwallowed vp in victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi> 1. Cor. 15.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Corinth. 15</note> You haue a great vordeale or aduauntage, for as much as you haue of your ſide, the moſt valiant, and moſt mightie, which ſhall neuer be able to be ouercome, yea, him that is Lord both of death &amp; of life. If death come vnto you, would deuour you, wil eate you vp, and ſwallowe you downe: yet can our Lord God, whiche is the right life it ſelfe, by his almightie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, and might, make you aliue againe, yea, in the middeſt of death, holde you by life, and make you liue for euer. For you ſhall not denie or refuſe to make this exchaunge, where you ſhall haue an euerlaſting and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13420:82"/> life, in ſtead of a tranſitorie, peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and labourious life, which is ful of miſerie, miſfortunes, and plagues. Let death take from you ſuch a life, as will laſt but the twinckling of an eye, which fléeth and paſſeth away like a ſhadowe, and our Lorde giue you an euerlaſting life. Amen.</p>
               <p>Thirtéene, Well nowe (dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) if your ſinne done and committed, do tempt you again, and your ſore miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déedes which you haue done, &amp; therefore would diſmay you, make you faint har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, heauie, &amp; penſiue, as though Chriſte would diſdaine you, bicauſe of your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſo not take you to him and to his fauour: then ſhall you ſet before your eyes, Chriſt your God and Lorde, as the holy ſcripture ſetteth him foorth, &amp; not follow your owne imagination, &amp; your reaſon. For in the holy Scripture you ſhal finde here and there, how mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous comfortable our Lorde Chriſte hath ben, at all times, to miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, howe loath he is to contemne or deſpiſe the miſerable, troubled, aſſaulted
<pb facs="tcp:13420:83"/> and ſorrowful ſinner, howe he doth not withdraw him ſelfe from them, or with drawe his helpe from them, whiche vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is a great comfort to al trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſinfull hearts. For behold and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the whole life of our Lorde Chriſt, then ſhall you not only perceiue that he hath not onely taken to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, one or two ſinners, &amp; hath taken pitie only vppon them, but he hath floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked into the middeſt of ſinners, wherby he might helpe them foorth of their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Firſt ſée his generation, his great grandfather, had he not many ſinners in his petigrée, as Iuda by name, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Manaſſes, Thamar, Rachab, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaba, and ſuch like, and very many moe. Wherefore doth our faithfull and good Lorde not be aſhamed, flée from ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful and penitent ſinners? why doth he not? Surely euen therfore, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all ſorrowfull ſinners ſhuld the more boldly haue a hartie reſort and recourſe vnto him, ſpecially ſéeing that he vppon ſuch ſinners, could take and ſhewe his truth, loue, and friendſhip, wherby they
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13420:83"/> might thereby winne and haue a liueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er paſſage and fréedome, to beholde all goodneſſe, all trueth and helpe, to be in this only bearer and carrier of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Beholde further, and looke vpon the birth of our lord Chriſt, in his birth. So ſoone as he was borne into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, he ſuffered him ſelfe to be ſéene, made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and to be knowne through the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels from heauen, to the poore people, ſpecially to the ſhepheards in the fielde, there muſt to them be ſhewed this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ioy, <hi>Behold, to you this day is borne a Sauiour.</hi> This ioy ſhal all people haue. There by his Angels is the innocent childe Ieſus giuen and declared, firſt to the poore ſhepheards, and after that to the whole world. But who be the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards? who be al people? ſurely al poore and miſerable ſinners, for whoſe ſake Chriſte came, and was borne, to helpe them out of their ſinnes. As alſo then ſuch a name was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ieſus, that is to ſay, a Sauiour that ſhall looſe his people from their ſinnes. Behold alſo, and ſée vprightly, wherfore
<pb facs="tcp:13420:84"/> was Chriſte at the eight day circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; ſo ſhed his innocent bloud? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the cauſe of poore and wretched ſinners. For Saint Paule ſaith, Gala. 4<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> that, <hi>Christ hath yealded him ſelfe therfore vnder the lawe and circumciſion, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he might deliuer them that were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the lawe.</hi> But who were more hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſnarled vnder the lawe, then the wretched ſinner? Sée yet to whom did Chriſt preach, and whome did he turne and conuert? Any other then the poore ſinner? To whome hath he friendlier ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, helped, or counſelled, made whole both in body and ſoule, then euen the poore, cumbred, and ſorrowfull ſinner? Mark alſo, with whom did Chriſt wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; goe about here through the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhe lande, and commaunded that they ſhould preach abroad his wholſome Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell? Surely with his welbeloued Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. But what were they? Wretched ſinners, as Matthewe, and likewiſe Peter: yea, did they not ſhewe them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues many times before Chriſte to be weake, worthy reproch, and fraile? How
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13420:84"/> oft hath our good Lord friendly rebuked them, taught them, taken in good part their weakneſſe, helped them, ſuffered, and borne with their faults and wants, and yet neither condemned them, nor caſt them away: but continually hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them after the beſt manner, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by at the laſt he might deliuer them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſinnes? There hath Chriſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued poore ſinners, in ſo much as he touched the hurt of their ſoul, but alſo the harmes of their body. Howe many thouſand men hath he many times fedd, when their hunger and néede went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his heart, and he tooke pitie of their miſerie? Oh, how many amongeſt them were miſerable ſinners, yea, infidels, and not worthy to haue and receiue ſuch goodneſſe at Gods hand? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hath he healed in their bodies, from agues, dropſie, and leproſie? Item, ſuch as were lame, crooked, blind, and haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and poſſeſſed with euill ſpirits? Yea, ſome he did raiſe from death it ſelfe, and alwayes ſhewed him ſelfe in all things, as the very true Sauiour of the whole
<pb facs="tcp:13420:85"/> world, by that meanes to bring the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels to faith, and to be ſhort, done the beſt to euery man, and ſhut out no man that had néede of his helpe, and had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon him, as the holy Euangeliſtes here and there do euidently and plainly declare. With which louing, comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and gratious examples of Chriſte, they ſhew vnto vs his great &amp; vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue and mercy, and declare &amp; ſhew the ſame vnto vs, with all diligence. Whereby we may learne to knowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right our Lorde Chriſte, ſpecially that he is therefore come to helpe miſerable ſinners, both in body and ſoule, both from temporall and euerlaſting hurte, whervnto ſathan hath brought al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. For, <hi>Christe is therefore come, that he ſhould deſtroy the worke of ſathan.</hi> 1. Ioh. 3.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hn. 3.</note> Whome ſo euer he helpeth in ſoule, him helpeth he alſo in body. And though he doe not alwayes hourely declare the ſame in this world, yet at Doomes day it will appeare, where he mightily hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the body out of duſt and mire, and all maner of deſtruction, for euermore.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13420:85"/> For he doth helpe in déede: yea, the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger he ſéemeth to withdraw his help, he ſheweth it afterward more mightily, therefore he is the only comfort and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, or helpe, to miſerable ſinners. Furthermore, Chriſte hath walked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſinners, in the middeſt of them, gone to ſinners, and hath runne after them, and deliuered them from their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, blindneſſe, and ſin. Shal not all this make worthily a mans heart merrie, and to haue a good conſcience, yea, a perfect aſſurance to all troubled and ſorrowful ſinners, that they may in all their néedes, ſinne, griefe, ſorrow, and death, with al their heartes run and come vnto ſuche a friendly Lorde, that wiſheth euery man good, prayeth for it, and doth it, that neuer hath driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from him any wretched ſinner? Yea, they at the laſt, in his death, were partakers with him on the croſſe, that he by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peciall foreſight of God, ſhoulde hang betwéene two grieuous offenders, in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken that he would willingly dye for miſerable ſinners, and for their cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:13420:86"/> willingly giue him ſelfe to death: yea, they had their part with him after his glorious reſurrection, to ſignifie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that he hath not forgotten miſerable ſinners, albeit that he hath conquered ſinne, death, hell, and ſathan him ſelfe, and yet might he well haue let alone this his conqueſt and triumph, and haue neglected vs miſerable ſinners. But he hath now ſought out miſerable ſinners, that he might helpe them and comfort them, as namely, vnbeleuing Thomas, the penitent Magdalene, and many mo, as he was going towards heauen, and nowe ſitteth at the right hande of God, in great glory and maieſtie: yet doth he not at all forget the poore ſinners, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened Sauls eyes, put away all his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and made of him a choſen witnes: yea, euen in theſe dayes, from time to time, doth our good faithfull Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſſing, take vp ſinners vnto him. For what doth he elſe at the right hand of God, then intreat, ſpeake for, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the miſerable ſinners, as a faithful Attorney, Mediatour, peacemaker, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:13420:86"/> highe prieſt, reconciler, and continuall king, as he hath taken vp al vs, you and me, and all ſorrowfull, repentant, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſinners? In mercy he giueth vs now daily his holy Ghoſt, which doth lighten and purifie our heartes, ſtrengtheneth them, giueth them power, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs in all our néedes. Therefore be of good comfort, ſéeing Chriſte nowe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, there can no miſerie come vnto you, ſéeing that Chriſte ſitteth on the right hand of God? Who can doe vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harme? Who can condemne vs? If Chriſt him ſelfe doe abſolue vs, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth vs to be quit, frée, looſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, and ſo pronounceth vs? To this Lord do I nowe commend you: let him not depart from your hart. For albeit I muſt depart hence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, &amp; muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to go to death, &amp; neither I nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world any more help you: yet wil not this Lorde depart from you, he is with you, and by you in your execution. And he is alſo faithful vnto you, and ſo gratious, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil go with you to death and will plucke you out againe from
<pb facs="tcp:13420:87"/> him, by his almightie power. Holde you vpon this Lorde by a ſtedfaſt faith, for I nowe commend you vnto him with all my heart.</p>
               <p>The fourtéenth, Dearely beloued, ſéeing you ſhal eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now be caried hence to the place of execution, &amp; ſhalbe ſéene of many folkes, take a merrie hearte vnto you, and ſpeake vnto the people, like a man: and louingly, and giue them warning before your death of theſe thrée pointes following. Firſt, that they will well thinke vppon and remember, the earneſt &amp; ſtrong righteouſnes of God, and take you before their eyes for an example of Gods Iuſtice, albeit his iudgement vppon you in compariſon of Gods righteous iuſtice and euerlaſting puniſhment, which ought worthily to ſtirre and moue all men to the feare of God, but (as it were) a flap with a foxe taile. Secondarily, that they fréely for Gods ſake, and of his mercie, euery of them all will forgiue you, forget your fault, and forgiue it, wherewith you at any time haue offended any man, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13420:87"/> it be in this place or in any other, for Ieſus ſake with all their heartes wil forgiue you, where and how ſoeuer you haue offended any of them, whether it be by word or déede. And that you alſo doe forgiue from the bottome of your hart willingly, both friend &amp; foe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſoeuer you haue béene offended.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that they will praye to our Lord God truely for you, whereby our Lord God, for his deare ſonns ſake, may giue vnto you a Chriſtian, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed paſſage out of this miſerie, by the ioynt working of the holy ghoſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>If the poore priſoner, by reaſon of weakenes, or for faint heart, cannot ſpeake himſelfe, and in the place of execution cannot warne the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſpeake vnto them himſelfe, then may his appointed miniſter, Or (as it is in ſome place) the hangman himſelf ſpeake vnto him, without danger, in this maner, and warne the people thus.</head>
               <p>WElbeloued, as you are now here preſent, and minde to behold this miſerable ſight: Firſt remember wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this poore priſoner ſtandeth here:
<pb facs="tcp:13420:88"/> ſurely not therefore, that in Gods ſight he is the greateſt ſinner amongſt vs: But to the intent that Almightie God, through this condemned man, will ſet before your eyes an example of his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſtice, whereby, by him you might be moued to a godly feare, to amend your life, and come before Gods anger, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and diſpleaſure, repent in time, abſtaine from your wicked life, and go in a godly liuing. Is it not thus welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued? ſay, Yea. Againe, the tyed priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner deſireth you all here heartily and humbly, that al you here together ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and generally, that you wil forgiue him whatſoeuer he hath ſpoken, done, or committed, whether it hath béene priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or openly, he is hartily ſorie for them all, he deſireth you all humbly and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly. Therefore he requireth that you wil beſtow alſo vppon him this mercie, that his Lord and God thorough Chriſt hath ſhewed vnto him, in that that he of méere grace and loue, hath forgiuen and forgotten all his ſinnes, &amp; that you haue a heartie compaſſion with him, not to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13420:88"/> be offended at him, but beare with his weakenes, helpe it, ſuffer it, and carrie it, as the Chriſtian rule willeth, where S. Paule the 6.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> to the Galathians ſaith thus: <hi>Euery one beare an others burthen, and ſo ſhall you fulfill the lawes of Chriſt.</hi> Is it not ſo my welbeloued? ſay, Yea.</p>
               <p>Thirdly and laſtly, this bounden pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner alſo requireth and prayeth you, for Gods mercie ſake, that you now at the houre of his departure out of this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for Chriſtian duetie and loue ſake, that you will inwardly from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottome of your heart, call vppon God and pray that he will increaſe in this poore man the faith of Chriſt, ſtrengthen him, and kéepe him therein for euer, and euer, wherby he may of grace enioy a bleſſed houre: and that the holy Ghoſt wil lead him, carrie him and guide him in the right way to ſaluation, and that he may obteine, at the length, euerlaſting peace and felicitie. We now require that this may be done. Therefore ſay, <hi>Our father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi> Doe you require this? ſay, Yea.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13420:89"/>
               <p>Well, now welbeloued, ſay you alſo, <hi>Our father, &amp;c.</hi> And yeld your ſelfe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to die, and ſay, Father thy will be done, &amp;c. Almightie God kéepe you going out of this miſerie from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth euermore. Amen.</p>
               <p>Say: Lord into thy hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſoule. Amen.</p>
               <p>¶ In ſome place while the Executioner doth lead foorth the poore man, and is about the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, ſome ſing in the meane ſeaſon. Nowe pray we the holy Ghoſt, as in Michſhen, and Sachſin, &amp;c. And in ſome place the miniſter in ths meane time ſaith the belefe. Whatſoeuer any man thinketh good and profitable, that may he ſet foorth and doe, and let the poore condemned man ſleepe in the Lorde, in holy hope, that whatſoeuer is now ſowen in ſhame and diſhonour, ſhall be at the laſt day in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honour and glory rayſed vp againe. Our Lord vouchſafe to preſerue vs all, one with an other, gratiouſly from ſinne, and keepe vs from ſinne and ſhame for euermore, through Chriſt Ieſus his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne, in the holy Ghoſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:13420:89"/>
               <head>A faithful and Chriſtian exhortation to repentaunce, and to leade a life in the feare <hi>of GOD.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Yrach amongſt his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in the 18. Chapter, warneth vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould in time refraine our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues from ſinne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent our ſelues, whileſt we can ſinne, where he alſo ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccle. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Doe not delay your repentance vntill you be ſicke, but amend your ſelues whilest you may ſin, driue not off the time to be good, nor tarrie not to better thy life, til the time of thy deth.</hi> In this matter he mindeth to ſet before our face the feare of God, whereby we ſhould not onely abſteine or forbeare to ſinne, but alſo for the reſidue of our life, kéepe our ſelues from ſinne with greate diligence: Specially, if we groundly &amp; déepely conſider, the earneſtneſſe and righteouſneſſe of God, howe our Lorde God is an earneſt enimie to ſinne, but
<pb facs="tcp:13420:90"/> ſpecially to ſuch ſins, as man eſtéemeth to be no ſinne, or will not acknowledge for ſinne, but will holde and take them as vertues and rightly done, and defend them as things well done, and ſo wholy goe forwarde, and continue in an vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant and ſtubborne life, whereby he falleth from thence without all ſorrowe and repentance, without ceaſſing grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly to ſinne againſt God his maker, in great contempt, deſpite, pride, and careleſneſſe, whereof then God taketh a great miſliking, and abhomination, ſo that he muſt néedes méete with ſuche of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, with all puniſhment, reuenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, &amp; plagues, eſpecially, with dearth, war, peſtilence, &amp;c. And God our Lorde bendeth him ſelfe alſo againſt all ſuche ſinnes, with all manner of power, with all his elements, as the aire, the fire, the water, and the earth, that we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with our eyes ſuch apparent anger and puniſhment of God, and muſt néeds taſte of them in all places. For from whence commeth ſuche warre, &amp; bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhead? Who is guiltie thereof? what is
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13420:90"/> the very cauſe? Is not ſinne, and our vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penitent, froward, and proude liuing? when man without all ſhame, without all feare of God, gréedily, wantonly, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly, and ſtubbornly doth ſin againſt our Lord God and maker? Whereby it commeth to paſſe, that many proude, wanton, filthy liuers be taken by God, and puniſhed very ſtraungly. Here lye in an houres ſpace many thouſandes ſlaine, there be many times many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds drowned: there many executed with the ſworde, fire, water, the whéele, and gallowes: There ſuffereth GOD many times within one halfe yere, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands dy on the peſtilence, there many to be hungerſtarued, here many thouſandes ſwallowed vp with earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes: there many periſhe in vprores and rebellions. And to be ſhort, no man is able to reckon or remember, howe many God muſt take and puniſhe, and likewiſe, cauſe to be made an example in the world, whereby ſuch fooliſh, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, and godleſſe wayes might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded and ſhunned. But who doeth
<pb facs="tcp:13420:91"/> earneſtly once think vpon theſe things? who doth turne him ſelfe, or ſtudie to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde theſe fearefull plagues of God? who ſetteth before his eyes ſuch exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods anger, thereby to amend his life? Surely very fewe come before ſuch execution and puniſhment of God, and in time turne them ſelues before ſuch fearefull iudgement of God, auoyd ſinne, and thinke to begin a godly and vertuous life. But in theſe dayes, the proude, froward, and wicked world, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thinketh of any of theſe things: And thereby it commeth to paſſe, that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lewde, ſo many falſe, ſo many ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, ſo much falſhood, ſo much ſinne &amp; filthineſſe beareth ſuch a great ſwinge, that at the length almightie God wil be ſo angrie, that within a while, there wil be no way to eſcape, no forbearing, no forgiueneſſe more take place, but God muſt in the end, without more pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or mercy, hurle the pitcher to the ground with great violence, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all grace and forbearing, daſh them together with thunder and lightening,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13420:91"/> with haile, and ſhewers, and with grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous feare and tempeſtuous ſtormes. Therfore on the behalfe of weaklings, and of ſuche as be fraile in their liuing and conuerſation, I thinke good to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe and warne them, that they doe not make of their weakneſſe and frailtie, a wicked cuſtome, leaſt at the length, they fal into an vnpenitent and blockiſh life and conuerſation, whereby God will be grieuouſly offended. Therefore it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them in time, beforehande, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their weake and ſinfull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, be ſorrie for them, and haue full purpoſe to amende their life, after that ſighe to obteine a heartie longing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes a godly life, and at the laſt to fight againſt ſin, &amp; to withſtand it with all our power, that there do not followe of our weakeneſſe an vnpenitent and blinde conuerſation, and leaſt they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably dye in that blindneſſe, and after that periſhe euerlaſtingly, from whiche our Lorde gratiouſly vouchſafe to kéepe vs, Amen. Againe, that ſuch weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in their conuerſation, receiue the
<pb facs="tcp:13420:92"/> time of grace, in ſeaſon, not loyteringly ſeeking for it, contemning it, nor be ſlouthfull therein. For, <hi>Here is the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table time, now is the day of grace,</hi> as holy Saint Paule writeth, in the ſecond to the Corinthians, the ſixt Chap.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 6.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let vs to our profite, and for our bleſſednes ſake, imbrace it in time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, and not ſuffer it to paſſe away from vs, or ſuffer ſuche an acceptable time of grace from God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very Iubilie yeare, yea, the golden yeare, for euer to flée in the winde, but rather pray for grace, in the right and in the time méete &amp; conuenient. Whereof Dauid ſaith in the 32. Pſal.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al. 32.</note> In which time, al holy, and ſuche as be weake in faith, doe ſéeke for our Lorde God, and pray for our Lorde God, and call for grace and forgiuing of their ſinnes, and hope vppon his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which is promiſed vnto vs in Chriſt Ieſus. Therefore let no man driue off too long, to better his life, but let euery man remember and thincke vppon the wrathe of God, and vppon his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: in time preuent or come before
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13420:92"/> them, driue not the time off till your death bed: for you are not ſure howe it will frame and fall out with you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you ſhall haue then your reaſon &amp; your wittes, or whether you ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to heare, or ſpeake your ſelfe, or whether you ſhall dye ſoudenly, and dye in the twinckling of an eye: wherefore, albeit we be all ſubiect to death, and that therefore we muſt all dye, yet doth our Lord God many times ſhorten ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a mans life before his time, chiefly bicauſe ſuch a man doth not remember his ſinfull and vnpenitent liuing, that he may let him ſmart, whereby he may win vnto him a good purpoſe to amend and better his life. I am afraide, there be very fewe that God taketh away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their time, bicauſe they be vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, whereby he may ſaue and deliuer them from great miſchaunces, and from the plagues at hand: and therefore God can take but ſmall pleaſure of ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as then only call vpon God, and ſue vnto him in the time of their miſhappes and puniſhmentes, and by and by, as
<pb facs="tcp:13420:93"/> ſoone as God our Lorde hath taken his correction from them againe, they alſo by and by forget it, and afterwarde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come worſe then euer they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Experience daily teacheth this: therefore, when ſo euer God helpeth vp ſuch a man, he helpeth a great offender only vp againe vpon his ſound limmes, ſo that afterwarde he is worſe then he was before. Therfore is this the cauſe, that God many times hath little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, luſt, or will, to helpe ſuche people, turne their puniſhment from them, or to take it from them. It is better they ly there ſick, or elſe buried in their graue, then that they ſhoulde more grieuouſly offend God, or any longer hurt good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Howbeit, if it ſo come to paſſe, that God lay hand vpon his owne, that is to ſay, weaklings and ſtraglers, and take them vnder his fatherly correction, looke well, whether you be one of thoſe or not, and that ye doe not ſuffer ſuch cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in vaine, but rather imagine &amp; learne, what our Lord GOD meaneth thereby, and what profite and good
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13420:93"/> our Lord God purpoſeth to ſet foorth by you.</p>
               <p>Firſt you ſhall knowe, that by this meanes, God will lead you to true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, after that giue you cauſe that you earneſtly ſéeke vnto him, and with your heart call vpon him, and from him onely looke for helpe and comfort: which be the very good and precious woorkes of the ſecond commaundement, where you are commaunded, that you ſhall not take the name of the Lord your God in vaine, which is then done, when you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly call vppon God in your neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, haue all your refuge for ſuccour to him, &amp; looke for all goodnes at his hands. Thoſe be moſt precious good woorkes, that doe paſſingly pleaſe GOD. After that, as ſoone as God hath helpen you, that you thancke him for his gratious helpe, thanke and praiſe his holy name, which is the right offering vp of thanks of the newe teſtament. As holy Dauid witneſſeth. Pſal. <hi>50.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> That is then the right true Gods ſeruice, to which Gods ſeruice our Lord God ſometime with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:13420:94"/> our minde and will, muſt force or driue vs with great croſſes and ſmarts, or elſe we would neuer walke in any ſuch good woorkes. Alſo we muſt laſtly, with holy Dauid in the <hi>119.</hi> Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſalme. 119.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and ſay: <hi>O Lord it is very profitable for me, that thou haſt humbled and brought me lowe, that I might know thy lawes.</hi> And hereof it commeth to paſſe, that our Lord God ſuffereth Sathan to trouble &amp; to vexe his, that he doth tempt them ſomtime with ſome ſpecial ſinne, and plagueth them therewith, whereby they be moued or driuen firſt to knowe themſelues, their weake nature &amp; frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: then to ſigh vnto God, to call vppon him and flie vnto him: they be our ſpurs and prickes whereby wée be driuen to God. And againe, that is our comfort, that God is ſo good, and that he can ſhew himſelfe ſo almightie, that he can turne the wickednes of his to the beſt. For he is ſuch a God, that he wil ſuffer no euil to be done, whereof he doeth not worke ſome good. But our Lord God is ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and many times doth ſhew it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13420:94"/> his, to ſhame the diuell, whereby he doeth very often breake and hinder Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans purpoſe, and vtterly deſtroy it. <hi>To this onely God and Lord he euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting thankes and praiſe, in Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Exhalt mich durch dein wort.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>Keepe me according to thy promiſe.</q>
                  <bibl>Pſalm. 119.</bibl>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13420:95"/>
               <head>An inſtruction to teache children howe they ought to goe to the Lordes Table.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>I haue herein ſomething varied from mine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, both becauſe hee is not named in the booke: and alſo for that it did in the woordes varied ſomething ſound contrary to our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Churche. I thought it meete to be added, becauſe it was bound with the former Dutch bookes, and neceſſary to be read to them that be in extremitie, if time will ſerue for it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, you muſt beléeue, if you will receiue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the body and bloud of Chriſt to your commoditie. After that muſt you trye or proue your ſelues, whether you doe worthily eate it, or take commoditie by it.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Faith.</head>
                  <p>Firſt of all you muſt well embrace the wordes of our louing Lord God Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13420:95"/> Chriſt, wherein he hath appointed vnto you his body and bloud to be a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, whereby you may be aſſured and certeined of his grace and bleſſed inheritaunce for euer, and with Chriſt and al good Chriſtians, to enioy their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in all thinges, and that you doe belong to the fellowſhip of Chriſt. For Chriſtian faith hath in it theſe 2. partes, Firſt, that by Gods grace we are made frée from all our ſinnes, and miſeries. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that we be partakers and felow woorkers of all the goodnes of God in Chriſt Ieſus. Theſe two partes be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed vnto vs in the Goſpel, &amp; belong to as many as beléeue the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit, to the intent euery man ſhould be the more ſure of his faith, and better certified that it belongeth vnto him, whatſoeuer is conteyned and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the Goſpel, Chriſt our Lord hath ordeined two Sacraments or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſignes: So that euery man that ſhould receiue them in a faſt and perfect faith, thereby ſhould be aſſured, that the two before remembred parts do belong
<pb facs="tcp:13420:96"/> vnto him, which he hath bound and tyed to no time, place or perſon: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be receiued, it is ſure that the faithfull receiue thoſe partes.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, beléeue ſtedfaſtly, that through Baptiſme almightie God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth forgiuing of all ſinnes, as we pray in our beliefe: I beléeue one Baptiſme for the forgiuenes of ſinnes. That is to ſay, I beléeue that through Gods mercy, by Ieſus Chriſt, in the holy Ghoſt only, my ſinnes altogether be forgiuen me, whereby I am aſſured and made ſafe in and by that onely Baptiſme. For albeit that the outward Baptiſme is but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly once done and miniſtred: yet doeth Gods worke, that he then doeth by it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide for euer and euer. This comforteth me at all times.</p>
                  <p>I beléeue alſo, that God by the deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the paſſion and death of Chriſt, by the holy Ghoſt hath made me all one with Chriſt and all good Chriſtians, and hath made me a member of the holy v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall congregation or Church: So that I haue felowſhip in all things with
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13420:96"/> all Gods holy children, &amp; that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer toucheth me, the ſame alſo toucheth them: and what ſo euer they haue, that is mine alſo.</p>
                  <p>And that ye ſhall not doubt hereof, he hath likewiſe giuen vnto you the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his body and of his bloud. When you receiue them, doubt not, but truely beleeue, that God in the power of his worde, vnder ſuch true ſignes, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in you the aboue remembred fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, according to the contentes of his worde, where he ſaith, <hi>Take, eate, this is my body, which ſhall be giuen for you.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Take and drinke all, for this is the cup of the newe Testament, which ſhall be ſhead for you, and for many, for forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</hi> Take holde of this worde, and comfort your ſelues therewith, for here doth Chriſt promiſe you, that you thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh his paſſion, or offering of his body, which was done vpon the croſſe, ſhal be one body with him, and with all his: ſo that he in you, and you in him, and all Saintes, ſhall be in one fellowſhippe. Therefore, ſaith he, his body is offered,
<pb facs="tcp:13420:97"/> or giuen for you. But that you ſhoulde not doubt that it is giuen vnto you, he ſaith thus, <hi>This is my body.</hi> When you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, then doubt not at all, that God by this ſacrament worketh aſſuredly, that you ſhal be partaker of the aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid fellowſhip, and that you are put in remembraunce, and aſſured thereof, as oft as you receiue the ſacrament.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe, when our Lord Ieſus ſaith, <hi>This is my bloud, &amp;c.</hi> beléeue ſtedfaſtly, without all manner of doubting, that Chriſtes bloud is ſhed for you, and your ſinnes thereby forgiuen. But that you ſhould be throughly perſuaded and ſafe that it is don for you, you haue a pledge or a ſacrament. As oft as you take it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your ſelfe, and thinke on our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, that euen God by this ſacrament worketh thoſe things in you, namely, that <hi>Christes bloud maketh you cleane from all your ſinnes.</hi> O what great comforte is in this ſacrament, therefore ought we very earneſtly to receiue it.</p>
                  <p>Further, deare childe, when you wil
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13420:97"/> receiue this ſacrament, thinke well vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the aboueſaid wordes of Chriſt, and ſtedfaſtly beléeue that God worketh in you that which the words do promiſe, &amp; ſay, Therefore doe I come vnto the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, bicauſe I beléeue, that his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was giuen for me, and bicauſe his bloud was ſhedde for me, whereby I am loſed from all my ſinnes, and am one body with him, in a full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect fellowſhip of all his goods, as a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>And bicauſe it is very hard to beleue ſuch high things, ſpecially that it ſhall auaile and profite me, being a poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and wretched caytife, therfore do I take with Chriſtes word the outwarde pledge, for the aſſuring and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my beléefe, that I may be ſure, that it is done in déede for me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Prouing.</head>
                  <p>But howe a man ſhall prepare or make him ſelfe ready to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Sainte Paule doth teache vs in his firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians, the
<pb facs="tcp:13420:98"/> 11.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Cor. 11.</note> Chapter, where he ſaith, <hi>Let a man try him ſelfe, and then eate of this bread, and drinke of this cuppe, &amp;c.</hi> that is, You ſhall not account nor reckon your ſelfe to be holy, not condemne other men, not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe other men, not be quarelling, but diligently looke about, howe néedie and miſerable you your ſelfe be, howe déepe you ſticke in ſinne, howe muche faith and other ghoſtly giftes you lacke, howe much you are bound and indebted vnto God, for many things, whereof you are not able to pay the leaſt.</p>
                  <p>Thinke vpon, and remember theſe and ſuche like pointes, howe you may haue remedy, and be holpen. And ſéeing that Chriſt in this ſacrament, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed you all theſe thinges, it behoueth you with earneſt deſire to ſéeke there. Here is the beſt proofe &amp; preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto this ſacrament, that a man with all ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtnes behold his own miſerie, griefe, ſinne, temptation, trouble, and begge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, &amp;c. whereby he might lay downe his Peacockes taile, and humble him ſelfe, and be as hungrie and gréedie after the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13420:98"/> helpe and grace of God, as a man is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to eate after ſower lettice. This is the right hunger to this meate. Oh that we knewe in what daunger we ſtand, what lacke we haue, howe déepe we ſticke, then would we be deſirous to this ſacrament, and make as much haſte therevnto, as the thirſtie Hart maketh to the waters.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For what cauſe a man ought to goe to the Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>NOt for cuſtome ſake, becauſe at Eaſter euery man goeth vnto it, not at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaundement of the Pope, or any other man: Not for our owne worthines, or becauſe we haue prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our ſelues: Not becauſe we ſhall make a good woorke of it, or make Gods ſeruice thereof: but onely becauſe that therby, in the power of Gods word, and pledge of Chriſt, I may receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance which my Lord Chriſt Ieſus by his deth hath purchaſed for me, &amp; beque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed me in his teſtament, ſpecially that
<pb facs="tcp:13420:99"/> I ſhould be frée from all my ſinnes, that I might be a brother and inheritour with Chriſt, and with Chriſte and all Chriſtians be a church and communal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: wherein, I ſhall haue felowſhippe with all Sainctes: ſo that, whatſoeuer Chriſt with al Chriſtians haue, is mine. And againe, to be ſhort, that Chriſte is mine, and I am his, and that I ſhal not depart from him, but ſtill abide where he is, and that I haue him with me, and by me, whether that I be in wealth or in woe: whether I be in proſperitie or in aduerſitie. And beſides this, he neuer forſaketh me, whether I be in néede, or in any other temptation, and that I ſhal beſide, enioy what other fruite ſoeuer belongeth to this Sacrament.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>When or howe often a man ought to goe to the Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>AS often as you be troubled &amp; temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through your ſinns in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, cumbred thorough the feare of death, or of hell, troubled by weakenes,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13420:99"/> either of body or of ſoule, or that you be faint harted in faith, or that you be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened with any weakenes or féeblenes whatſoeuer it be, wherewith the diuel, the world, or the fleſh wil hinder you in your inheritance or bleſſedneſſe, ſéeke here comfort in the word and ſigne gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in this ſacrament by Chriſt, which he hath at his laſt ſupper left vnto you, where vppon he died, and haue no doubt at all, but that God in temptation wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth whatſoeuer the word and token, or ſigne do promiſe or bring. Herein let no mans fantaſie or imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make you forſake the right way.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What beleeue you of this ſacrament?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>J</hi> Beléeue, that there is, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of Chriſte, giuen vnto me the body and bloud of Chriſte, (though in ſuch ſorte as reaſon can not perceiue:) So that God almightie worketh in me, and towards me, in the receiuing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all that which my Lorde Ieſus hath there promiſed, as ſpecially that his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:13420:100"/> maketh me cleane, and maketh my body to be in fellowſhippe with Chriſt, and with all Chriſtians, and that his bloud doth waſhe away all my ſinnes. Therefore I doubt nothing at all, but that I doe receiue there the body &amp; bloud of Chriſte, albeit that by reaſon I can not perceiue how, or by what manner, and way, neyther is it neceſſarie for me to knowe. It was ſufficient to Chriſtes Apoſtles, that they knewe that Chriſte was riſen from death, albeit they could not tell nor perceiue how he came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, the doores being ſhut in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What is Christes Supper, or Gods boord.</head>
                  <p>IT is nothing elſe, but the Teſtament of Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde, which he made and ordeined before his paſſion and death, for all them that beléeue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and for them that in their bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme through the deſeruing of his death and reſurrection, be made frée from the power and kingdome of the diuell, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13420:100"/> choſen to be Gods children, or inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the kingdome of heauen. To them hath he promiſed, and giueth in this ſacrament truely, his body and his bloud for their comfort, wherby they be fully aſſured, &amp; made certeine by faith in their conſciences, that he will giue vnto them all the goodneſſe of God, and make them coheires with him, &amp; with the whole Chriſtian congregation, in a perfect fellowſhip of all Saints. For in as much as Chriſte hath promiſed and giuen vnto them his body and his bloud, why can he not giue vnto them al other good things that he hath, either in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or in earth? Herevpon ſhal his body and his bloud certenly be receiued, to aſſure vs, that our louing Lord Chriſt wil not betray vs, but make vs with him to be Lordes and inheritours of all the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Whoſoeuer will receiue the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Christ, ought to know how to anſwere to the fiue queſtions folowing.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13420:101"/>
                  <p> The first Question.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 WHerefore receiue you this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</p>
                  <p>Aunſwere.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, bicauſe I may be a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heire with Chriſte, and haue fellowſhip with him, with all holy Saintes, and with all good Chriſtians, with them to ſuffer and to dye.</p>
                  <p>Question.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 What doe you beléeue, or what doe you confeſſe is in this ſacrament?</p>
                  <p>Anſwere.</p>
                  <p>When I receiue the Sacrament, I beleeue, that vnder breade and wine, I receiue the body and bloud of Chriſte: but it is not ſufficient that I know, but alſo I muſt beléeue, that my lord Chriſt hath giuen me them for a perfect ſigne and token, ſeale and teſtament.</p>
                  <p>Question.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 What be the wordes of this Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which our Lord Ieſus did vſe?</p>
                  <p>Anſwere.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus ſaid the Lord to his Apoſtles, when he gaue vnto them this breade,</hi>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:13420:101"/> Take ye, and eate ye, This is my body, which ſhall be giuen for you. <hi>And when he gaue them the cup, he ſaide,</hi> Drinke you all of this, This is my bloude of the newe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whiche ſhall be ſhead for you, and for many, for the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. Do this in the remembrance of me.</p>
                  <p>Question.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Wherefore do you take that token or ſigne, ſéeing that faith is ſufficient?</p>
                  <p>Anſwere.</p>
                  <p>I receiue the ſignes and tokens ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, bicauſe I may ſtrengthen my faith, not bicauſe I doubt in my beléefe: but bicauſe God hath giuen me the ſigne, with the word, of his tender grace and mercy. Therefore I will not deſpiſe to vſe and acquaint my ſelfe with them.</p>
                  <p>Question.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 How will you vſe the Sacrament?</p>
                  <p>Anſwere.</p>
                  <p>I will eate and drinke, and beléeue this word, which he ſpake vnto his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, when he gaue them this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. We ought to take theſe comfortable promiſes, with a faithfull heart.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13420:102"/>
               <head>A breefe declaration of the Lordes Prayer, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Our Father.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſte we muſt conſider, wherfore we pray, what is meant by wherefore, the time, &amp; occaſion doeth always bring them. But bicauſe we ſhould not be carefull, nor trouble our ſelues, wherfore we ſhould pray, ſéeing we be now in ſuch extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that many troubles daily fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs, and that from day to day, the longer the worſe, although we ſhuld very much pray. For, <hi>The diuell is a liar, and a murtherer.</hi> And neither is the Pope nor the Turke, nor many other tyrants, which be againſt Gods worde idle. Beſides this, we haue experience that euery aduerſarie is ſufficient of it ſelfe, though this generall trouble were not, therefore we haue euery where oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſufficient, which may driue vs to prayer.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:13420:102"/>
               <p>Whoſoeuer therefore cannot remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber all our neceſſities, let him take in hand and haue before his eyes, the holy prayer of our Lord, called <hi>Our Father,</hi> in it be ſeuen petitions. In which be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined all troubles, &amp; things neceſſarie.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the firſt prayer, <hi>Hallowed be thy name,</hi> we pray for the holy Goſpel, for all true preachers, againſt all hereſie, &amp; miſbeléeuers, againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, heathen, Turke &amp; Pope. For all theſe blaſpheme and ſlander Gods name, and vnhallow him: that God will cut them ſhort, ſend good preachers, &amp; kéepe his word cleane and pure againſt all hereſie, &amp; make vs apt hearers. This is to intend or before to meane ſomewhat.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the ſecond, <hi>Thy kingdome come,</hi> we praye, that the kingdome of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, &amp; of death may be deſtroyed. That is a great and a large petition, for in it is conteyned the whole kingdome of the diuel, that it would pleaſe God to make an end of it, and ſet vp in vs and al men his owne kingdome, through his word, and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13420:103"/>3. In the third petition, <hi>Thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen,</hi> we deſire, that all their willes be diſappointed which ſtriue againſt Gods gratious wil. That is a great &amp; vnſufferable prayer againſt the diuel and all wicked people, &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellouſly putteth back many perils and miſfortunes, whiche the diuel and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people imagine and ſett abroche, if they were not thorough this petition diſappointed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the fourth petition, <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread,</hi> wée do praye for the Quéenes maieſtie, for our magiſtrates, for our elders, for our wiues and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for our meate and drinke, for the fruite in the field, for peace, and for ſuch thinges as we lacke toward the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning of this preſent life, euery one in their vocation, that God will bleſſe them therein, giue them good fortune, and kéepe them from all miſfortune mercifully.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the fifte petition, <hi>Forgiue vs our ſinnes, as wee forgiue them that treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs,</hi> we deſire that God will be
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13420:103"/> gratious to vs, to turne from vs his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whiche we haue deſerued, &amp; not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs for our wickednes: and that he will deale gratiouſly with vs, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent we, from day to day, maye waxe better, and that we maye liue after his holy will, and liue friendly one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and that euery of vs maye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue an other their offences.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In the ſixte petition, <hi>Lead vs not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation,</hi> we pray that GOD will come and helpe all troubled heartes, not ſuffer them to ſticke in temptation, but help them out therof gratiouſly through his word and holy ſpirite: and that he wil vouchſafe to deſtroy the diuels pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and might.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In the ſeuenth petition, <hi>But deliuer vs from the euill,</hi> wée praye for a good houre, that our Lord God will take vs out of this miſerie, with grace, and make vs bleſſed for euer.</p>
               <p>Thus, in the Lords prayer, are plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully al thinges conteyned, whatſoeuer by any meanes ſhal vexe or trouble vs, or els whatſoeuer is méeteſt and moſt
<pb facs="tcp:13420:104"/> neceſſarie for vs. Therefore the firſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that we purpoſe or intende ſomething, wherefore we will pray, that will Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God ſurely giue. For the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement is plainly there, that <hi>Wee muſt pray,</hi> &amp; the promiſe is alſo there, that <hi>We ſhalbe certeinely and ſurely heard.</hi> And our mercifull Lord Chriſte him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath ſett foorth vnto vs, both the words and the manner how we ſhal pray: in the which all things neceſſarie for vs be conteined.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13420:104"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
